<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>Blog blog("Baptiste Wicht"); (Posts about asgard)</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/</link><description></description><atom:link rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" href="http://baptiste-wicht.com/categories/asgard.xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 04 Jun 2017 20:17:46 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Asgard: Home Automation project</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2016/08/asgard-home-automation-project.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I have updated my asgard project to make it finally useful for me, so I figured
I'd present the project now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Asgard is my project of home automation based on a Raspberry Pi. I started this
project after Ninja Blocks kickstarter company went down and I was left with
useless sensors. So I figured why not have fun creating my own :P I know there
are some other projects out there that are pretty good, but I wanted to do some
more low level stuff for once, so what the hell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, everything is written in C++, no surprise here. The project is built
upon a server / drivers architecture. The drivers and the server are talking via
network sockets, so they can be on different machines.  The server is displaying
the data it got on a web interface and also provide a way to trigger actions of
drivers either from the web interface or through the integrated rules engine.
The data are stored in a database, accessed with CPPSqlite3 (probably going to
be replaced by sqlcpp11) and the web server is handled with mongoose (with a c++
interface).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I must mention that most of the web part of the project was made by a student of
mine, Stéphane Ly, who work on it as part of his study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a picture of the Raspberry Pi system (not very pretty ;) ):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Asgard automation system hardware" class="align-center" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/asgard_hardware.jpg"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I plan to try to fit at least some of it on a nicer box with nicer cables and
such. Moreover, I also plan to add real antennas to the RF transmitter and
receiver, but I haven't received them so far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="sensors"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Sensors&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;asgard support several sensors:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;DHT11 Temperature/Humdity Sensor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;WT450 Temperature/Humdity Sensor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;RF Button&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;IR Remote&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CPU Temperature Sensor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can see the sensors data displayed on the web interface:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Asgard automation system home page" class="align-center" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/asgard_home.png"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="actions"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are currently a few actions provided by the drivers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wake-On-Lan a computer by its MAC Address&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ITT-1500 smart plugs ON and OFF&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kodi actions: Pause / Play / Next / Previous on Kodi&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are the rules engine:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Asgard automation system rules page" class="align-center" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/asgard_rules.png"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="my-home-automation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;My home automation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm currently using this system to monitor the temperature in my appartment.
Nothing great so far because I don't have enough sensors yet. And now, I'm also
using a wireless button to turn on my power socket, wait 2 seconds and then
power on my Kodi Home Theater with wake on lan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's nothing fancy so far, but it's already better than what I had with Ninja
Blocks, except for the ugly hardware ;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="future"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Future&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are still tons of work on the project and on integration in my home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I'm really dissatisfied with the WT450 sensor, I've ordered new Oregon sensors to try to do better.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I've ordered a few new sensors: Door intrusion detector and motion detector&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The rules system needs to be improve to support multiple conditions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I plan to add a simple state system to the asgard server&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are a lot of refactorings necessary in the code and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, I don't know when I'll work on this again, my work on this project is
pretty episodic to say the least.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="code"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Code&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The code is, as always, available on Github. There are multiple repositories:
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/search?q=user%3Awichtounet+asgard"&gt;all asgard repositories&lt;/a&gt;.
It's not that much code for now, about 2000 lines of code, but some of it may be
useful. If you plan to use the system, keep in mind that it was never tested out
of my environment and that there is no documentation so far, but don't hesitate
to open Issues on Github if you have questions or post a comment here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>asgard</category><category>Home Automation</category><category>Personal</category><category>projects</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2016/08/asgard-home-automation-project.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 27 Aug 2016 20:28:16 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>