<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title>Blog blog("Baptiste Wicht"); (Posts about budgetwarrior)</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/</link><description></description><atom:link rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" href="http://baptiste-wicht.com/categories/budgetwarrior.xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2017 18:57:32 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Budgetwarrior: Track assets and portfolio, savings rates and auto-completion</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2017/10/budgetwarrior-track-assets-portfolio-savings-rates-auto-completion.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;This last month, I've been reading quite a few blogs about personal finance and
I've decided to integrate more features into budgetwarrior. This post is about
three new features that I've integrated. It's not yet a new release, so if you
want to test this version, you'll have to compile it from the &lt;em&gt;master&lt;/em&gt; branch on
Git.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As it was last time, the values on my screenshots have all been randomized.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have several assets with different distributions, I believe it is a great
value to have them all shown at the same time. Especially if you want to change
the distribution of your portfolio or if you plan big changes in it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="track-assets"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Track assets&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first feature I've added is a feature to precisely track each of your assets
independently. And you can also track the allocation of your portfolio in terms
of stocks, bonds and cash. The tool also lets you set the desired distribution
of your assets and will compute the difference that you should make in order to
comply to your desired distribution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, you need to define all your asset classes (your accounts, funds, and
stocks, ...) and their distribution with &lt;code&gt;budget asset add&lt;/code&gt;. It also
supports to set a currency. The default currency is now CHF, but you can set it
in the configuration file, for instance &lt;code&gt;default_currency=USD&lt;/code&gt;. You can
see your assets using &lt;code&gt;budget asset&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="View of your assets" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/budgetwarrior_assets.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can then set the value of your assets using &lt;code&gt;budget asset value add&lt;/code&gt;.
The system will save all the values of your assets. For now, only the last value
is used in the application to display. In the future, I plan to add new reports
for evolution of the portfolio over time. You can see your current net worth
with the &lt;code&gt;budget asset value&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="View of your portfolio" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/budgetwarrior_asset_values.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The different currencies will all be converted to the default currency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="savings-rate"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Savings rate&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second change I did is to compute the savings rate of each month and year.
The savings rate is simply the portion of your income that you are able to save
each month. The savings rate for a year is simple the average of the savings
rate of each month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The savings rate of the month can be seen with &lt;code&gt;budget overview month&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Savings rate of the month" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/budgetwarrior_savings_rate.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The saving rates of each month can also be seen in the overview of the year with
&lt;code&gt;budget overview year&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Savings rate of the year" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/budgetwarrior_savings_rate_year.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This shows the savings rate of each month, the average of the year and the
average of the current year up to the current month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The savings rate is a very important metric of your budget. In my case, it's
currently way too low and made me realize I really need to save more. Any
savings rate below 10% is too low. There are no rule as too much it should be,
but I'd like to augment mine to at least 20% next year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="auto-completion"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Auto-completion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last feature is mostly some quality-of-life improvement. Some of the inputs
in the console can now be completed. It's not really auto-completion per se, but
you can cycle through the list of possible values using the UP and DOWN.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This makes it much easier to set some values such as asset names (in
&lt;code&gt;budget asset value add&lt;/code&gt; for instance), account names and objective types
and sources. I'm trying to make the input of values easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="conclusion"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't know exactly what else will be integrated in this feature, but I may
already improve some visualization for asset values. If I learn something new
about personal finance that I may integrate in the tool, I'll do it as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are interested by the sources or want to install this version,
you can download them on Github:
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/wichtounet/budgetwarrior"&gt;budgetwarrior&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new features are in the &lt;em&gt;master&lt;/em&gt; branch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have a suggestion for a new features or you found a bug, please post an
issue on Github, I'd be glad to help you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have any comment, don't hesitate to contact me, either by letting a
comment on this post or by email.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>budgetwarrior</category><category>C++</category><category>Linux</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2017/10/budgetwarrior-track-assets-portfolio-savings-rates-auto-completion.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2017 17:40:14 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>budgetwarrior 0.4.2 - Budget summary and improved fortune reports</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2017/09/budgetwarrior-042-budget-summary-improved-fortune-reports.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Almost three years ago, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2014/09/budgetwarrior-041-expense-templates-and-year-projection.html"&gt;I published the version 0.4.1 of budgetwarrior&lt;/a&gt;. Since then, I've been using this tool almost every day to manage my personal budget. This is the only tool I use to keep track of my expenses and earnings and it makes a great tool for me. I recently felt that it was missing a few features and added them and polished a few things as well and release a new version with all the new stuff. This new version is probably nothing fancy, but a nice upgrade of the tool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don't pay too much attention to the values in the images since I've randomized
all the data for the purpose of this post (new feature, by the way :P).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="new-summary-view"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;New summary view&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've added a new report with &lt;code&gt;budget summary&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="/images/budgetwarrior_042_summary.png" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/budgetwarrior_042_summary.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This view gives concise information about the current state of your accounts. It
also gives information about your yearly and monthly objectives. Finally, it
also gives information about the last two fortune values that you've set.
I think this make a great kind of dashboard to view most of the information. If
your terminal is large enough, the three parts will be shown side by side.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="improved-fortune-report"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Improved fortune report&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've made a few improvements to the &lt;code&gt;budget fortune&lt;/code&gt; view:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="/images/budgetwarrior_042_fortune.png" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/budgetwarrior_042_fortune.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It now display the time between the different fortune values and it compute the
average savings (or avg losses) per day in each interval and in average from the
beginning of the first value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="various-changes"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Various changes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The balance does not propagate over the years anymore. This should mainly change
the behaviour of &lt;code&gt;budget overview&lt;/code&gt;. I don't think it was very
smart to propagate it all the time. The balance now starts at zero for each
year. If you want the old system, you can use the multi_year_balance=true option
in the .budgetrc configuration file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The recurring expenses do not use an internal configuration value. This does not
change anything for the behaviour, but means that if you sync between different
machines, it will avoid a lot of possible conflicts :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fixed a few bugs with inconsistency between the different views and reports.
Another bug that was fixed is that &lt;code&gt;budget report&lt;/code&gt; was not always displaying the
first month of the year correctly, this is now fixed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The graphs display in &lt;code&gt;budget report&lt;/code&gt; are now automatically adapted to width of
your terminal. Finally, the &lt;code&gt;budget overview&lt;/code&gt; command also displays more
information about the comparison with the previous month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="installation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Installation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are on Gentoo, you can install it using layman:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
layman -a wichtounet
emerge -a budgetwarrior
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are on Arch Linux, you can use this &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/StreakyCobra/aur-budgetwarrior"&gt;AUR repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For other systems, you'll have to install from sources:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
git clone --recursive git://github.com/wichtounet/budgetwarrior.git
cd budgetwarrior
make
sudo make install
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="conclusion"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A brief tutorial is available on Github: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/wichtounet/budgetwarrior/wiki/Start-tutorial"&gt;Starting guide&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are interested by the sources, you can download them on Github:
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/wichtounet/budgetwarrior"&gt;budgetwarrior&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have any suggestion for a new feature or an improvement to the tool or
you found a bug, please post an issue on Github, I'd be glad to help you. You
can post a comment directly on this post :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have any other comment, don't hesitate to contact me, either by letting a
comment on this post or by email.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope that this application can be useful to some of you command-line adepts :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>budgetwarrior</category><category>C++</category><category>Gentoo</category><category>Linux</category><category>Releases</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2017/09/budgetwarrior-042-budget-summary-improved-fortune-reports.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 14 Sep 2017 18:42:39 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>budgetwarrior 0.4.1 - Expense templates and year projection</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2014/09/budgetwarrior-041-expense-templates-and-year-projection.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I've been able to finish the version 0.4.1 of budgetwarrior before I though :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="expense-templates"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Expense templates&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The "most useful" new feature of this release is the ability to create template
for expenses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For that, you can give an extra parameter to budget expense add:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
budget expense add template name
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will works exactly the same as creating a new expense expect that it will
be saved as a template. Then, the next time you do:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
budget expense add template name
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A new expense will be created with the date of the day and with the name and
amount saved into the template. You can create as many templates as you want as
long as they have different names. You can see all the templates you have by
using 'budget expense template'. A template can be deleted the exact same as an
expense with 'budget expense delete id'.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think this is very useful for expense that are made several times a month, for
instance a coffee at your workplace. The price should not change a lot and it is
faster to just use the template name rather than entering all the information
again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="year-prediction"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Year prediction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can now see what would be next year if you changed a bit your expenses. For
instance, how much would you still have at the end of the year if you increased
your house expenses by 20% and reduced your insurances by 5% ?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 'budget predict' can be used for that purpose. You can enter a multiplier
for each account in your budget and a new year will be "predicted" based on
the expenses of the current year multiplied by the specified multiplier:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="/images/budget_041_prediction.png" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/budget_041_prediction.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that this feature can be very useful if you want to estimate how your
budget will be for moving to a more expensive house or another insurance for
instance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="various-changes"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Various changes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two accounts can be merged together with the 'budget account migrate' command.
This command will move all expenses from an account to another and adapt the
amount of the target account. The source account will be deleted. This supports
migrated accounts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 'budget wish list' command will now display the mean accuracy of your
predictions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You don't need Boost anymore for this project. The only remaining dependency is
libuuid. I will perhaps remove it in the next version since the UUID are not
used in the application for now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The command 'budget gc' will clean the IDs of all your data in order to fill the
holes and make all the IDs contiguous. It is mostly a feature for order-freaks
like me who do not like to have holes in a sequence of identifiers ;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was a bug in the monthly report causing the scale to be displayed
completely moved, it is now fixed:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/wichtounet/budgetwarrior/develop/screenshots/budget_report.png" src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/wichtounet/budgetwarrior/develop/screenshots/budget_report.png"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="installation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Installation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are on Gentoo, you can install it using layman:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
layman -a wichtounet
emerge -a budgetwarrior
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are on Arch Linux, you can use this &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/StreakyCobra/aur"&gt;AUR repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For other systems, you'll have to install from sources:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
git clone git://github.com/wichtounet/budgetwarrior.git
cd budgetwarrior
make
sudo make install
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="conclusion"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are interested by the sources, you can download them on Github:
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/wichtounet/budgetwarrior"&gt;budgetwarrior&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have a suggestion for a new features or you found a bug, please post an
issue on Github, I'd be glad to help you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have any comment, don't hesitate to contact me, either by letting a
comment on this post or by email.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>budgetwarrior</category><category>C++</category><category>Gentoo</category><category>Linux</category><category>Releases</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2014/09/budgetwarrior-041-expense-templates-and-year-projection.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 21 Sep 2014 18:53:53 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>budgetwarrior 0.4 - Enhanced wish list and aggregate</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2014/07/budgetwarrior-04-enhanced-wish-list-and-aggregate.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I've just released a new version of my command-line budget manager:
budgetwarrior 0.4.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="enhanced-aggregate-overview"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Enhanced aggregate overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aggregate overviews have been greatly improved. First, there is now a
&lt;em&gt;budget overview month&lt;/em&gt; command that groups all expenses of amonth together.
Here is a possible output:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="/images/budget_04_aggregate_month.png" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/budget_04_aggregate_month.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also possible to use &lt;em&gt;--full&lt;/em&gt; option to also aggregate together the different
accounts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="/images/budget_04_aggregate_month_full.png" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/budget_04_aggregate_month_full.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another new option is &lt;em&gt;--no-group&lt;/em&gt; that disables the grouping by categories:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="/images/budget_04_aggregate_month_full_ng.png" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/budget_04_aggregate_month_full_ng.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, the separator of categories can now be configured with &lt;em&gt;--separator=&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All these options can also be set in the configuration with these options:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;aggregate_full : If set to true, does the same as the --full option.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;aggregate_no_group : If set to true, does the same as the --no-group option.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;aggregate_separator : Sets the separator for grouping.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="enhanced-wish-list"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Enhanced wish list&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The wishes management has also been improved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, each wish can now be set an Urgency and Importance level. This is now
shown in wish status as simple indicators:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="/images/budget_04_wish_status.png" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/budget_04_wish_status.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, the accuracy of the estimation compared to the paid amount is shown in
&lt;em&gt;wish list&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="/images/budget_04_wish_list.png" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/budget_04_wish_list.png"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="various-changes"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Various changes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Objective status now shows more information about the status of the objectives:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="/images/budget_04_objective_status.png" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/budget_04_objective_status.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The versioning module has been improved. The &lt;em&gt;versioning sync&lt;/em&gt; does now perform
a commmit as well as pull/push. &lt;em&gt;versioning push&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;versioning pull&lt;/em&gt; and
&lt;em&gt;versioning status&lt;/em&gt; commands have been added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;budget version&lt;/em&gt; command shows the version of budgetwarrior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aliases a now available to make shorted commands:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;budget sync -&amp;gt; budget versioning sync&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;budget aggregate -&amp;gt; budget overview aggregate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="installation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Installation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are on Gentoo, you can install it using layman:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
layman -a wichtounet
emerge -a budgetwarrior
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are on Arch Linux, you can use this &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/StreakyCobra/aur"&gt;AUR repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For other systems, you'll have to install from sources:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
git clone git://github.com/wichtounet/budgetwarrior.git
cd budgetwarrior
make
sudo make install
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="conclusion"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are interested by the sources, you can download them on Github:
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/wichtounet/budgetwarrior"&gt;budgetwarrior&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have a suggestion or you found a bug, please post an issue on Github.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have any comment, don't hesitate to contact me, either by letting a
comment on this post or by email.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>budgetwarrior</category><category>C++</category><category>Gentoo</category><category>Git</category><category>Linux</category><category>Releases</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2014/07/budgetwarrior-04-enhanced-wish-list-and-aggregate.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 06 Jul 2014 08:59:55 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>budgetwarrior 0.3.1 - Git versioning and easier creation</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2014/05/budgetwarrior-031-git-versioning-easier-creation.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I've finished a new version of budgetwarrior: budgetwarrior 0.3.1&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Changes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most interesting change is the ability to estimate the date when it is a good time to buy something from the wish list. This is done with the &lt;em&gt;budget wish estimate&lt;/em&gt; command: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="budget wish estimate" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/budget_031_wish_estimate.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This command gives you two dates for each wish in your list. The first is the date wating for each yearly objectives to be fullfilled. The second one considers only the monthly objectives. For now on, no estimation of expenses is made for the future months. It means that the estimation is made as if there were no expenses in the future months. I'll try to improve that by considering averages of expenses in the previous months to make it more reliable. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still on the wish module, you can now mark your wishes as paid instead of deleting them. This helps you keep track of the prices of your wishes. This is done with the &lt;em&gt;budget wish paid id&lt;/em&gt; command. Finally, the totals of the unpaid wishes and of the paid wishes is displayed in &lt;em&gt;budget wish list&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another helpful change is the ability to set a date relative to today's date when creating an expense or an earning. For instance, you can create an expense one month before (-1m) or in one year ((+1y) or yesterday (-1d): &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="new date selection mechanism" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/budget_031_date_selection.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, you can also still set the date manually. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last major change is the addition of a new module: &lt;em&gt;budget versioning&lt;/em&gt;. This module helps you manipulate you budget directory with Git. There are two new commands: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;budget versioning save&lt;/em&gt;: Commit the current changes with a default message (Update). &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;budget versioning sync&lt;/em&gt;: Pull the changes from the remote directory and push the local changes. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will only works if you have already configured your budget directory to use Git. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope you'll found these changes interesting :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are interested by the tool, you can download it on Github: &lt;a href="https://github.com/wichtounet/budgetwarrior"&gt;budgetwarrior&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have a suggestion or you found a bug, please post an issue on the github project: &lt;a href="https://github.com/wichtounet/budgetwarrior"&gt;https://github.com/wichtounet/budgetwarrior&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have any comment, don't hesitate to contact me, either by letting a comment on this post or by email.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>budgetwarrior</category><category>C++</category><category>Git</category><category>Linux</category><category>projects</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2014/05/budgetwarrior-031-git-versioning-easier-creation.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 10 May 2014 14:45:43 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>budgetwarrior 0.3.0 - Objective and wish management</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2014/02/budgetwarrior-0-3-0-objective-wish-management.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I'm pleased to announce the release of another budgetwarrior release, the version 0.3.0.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Changes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This version contains several important changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first one is the addition of a new module to manage objectives. You can add objective with &lt;em&gt;budget objective add). &lt;/em&gt;For instance, you can add an objective saying you want to save 10000$ a year or 200$ a month. When you set your objectives, budget warrior computes how well you complete them. For instance, here is the status of my objectives:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://baptiste-wicht.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/Screenshot-from-2014-02-02-113057-e1391337197470.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="Objective Status" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/Screenshot-from-2014-02-02-113057-e1391337197470-300x83.png" title="Objective Status"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another module has been added to manage wishes. You can add wishes to budgetwarrior (&lt;em&gt;budget wish add&lt;/em&gt;) and then budgetwarrior will tell you if it is a good time to buy them. Here is an example of wish status:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.baptiste-wicht.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/Screenshot-from-2014-02-02-113814.png"&gt;&lt;img class="size-medium wp-image-2665" alt="Wish Status" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/Screenshot-from-2014-02-02-113814-e1391337576857-300x96.png" width="300" height="96"&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Wish Status&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The diagnostics tells you where the money will be taken: On savings, on year savings or on month savings (ideal case). It also checks the objectives to see if the payment doesn't break the fulfillment of some of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For complete diagnostics, it is necessary to you register your fortune (&lt;em&gt;budget fortune check&lt;/em&gt;), ideally once a month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, this is only a tool, you should not only use that to decide when to buy something, but it may have a good point of view ;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, the version also have other smaller changes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When you make an error when creating a new item (expense, earning, ...), the tool now lets you retry without losing what you typed before.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Confirmation messages are now shown after each modification command (delete, add and edit).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The license has been changed from Boost to MIT. The sense is almost the same, but the MIT is more well known and I thought it would be easier for people to know what this means.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There have several changes to the code base, but that doesn't impact the usage of the tool.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope you'll found these changes interesting :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are interested by the tool, you can download it on Github: &lt;a title="budgetwarrior repository" href="https://github.com/wichtounet/budgetwarrior"&gt;budgetwarrior&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is now Gentoo and Arch Linux installation packages available for ease of installation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have a suggestion or you found a bug, please post an issue on the github project: &lt;a title="https://github.com/wichtounet/budgetwarrior" href="https://github.com/wichtounet/budgetwarrior"&gt;https://github.com/wichtounet/budgetwarrior&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have any comment, don't hesitate to contact me, either by letting a comment on this post or by email.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>budgetwarrior</category><category>C++</category><category>Linux</category><category>projects</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2014/02/budgetwarrior-0-3-0-objective-wish-management.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2014 08:21:29 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>budgetwarrior 0.2.1 - Minor changes and Gentoo ebuild</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2014/01/budgetwarrior-0-2-1-minor-changes-gentoo-ebuild.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I've released a new version of budgetwarrior, the release 0.2.1. budgetwarrior is a simple command line application to manage a personal budget.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The version 0.2.1 contains several bug fixes about archived accounts and bug fixes for budget across several years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The application as well as the source code is available online: &lt;a href="https://github.com/wichtounet/budgetwarrior"&gt;https://github.com/wichtounet/budgetwarrior&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've created Gentoo ebuilds for this application. They are available on my Portage overlay: &lt;a href="https://github.com/wichtounet/portage-overlay"&gt;https://github.com/wichtounet/portage-overlay&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Gentoo Installation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Edit overlays section of /etc/layman/layman.cfg. Here's an example:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;overlays: http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/overlays/repositories.xml
           http://github.com/wichtounet/portage-overlay/raw/master/repository.xml&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Sync layman&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;layman -S&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Add the overlay:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;layman -a wichtounet&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Install budgetwarrior&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;emerge budgetwarrior&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you find any issues with the tool, don't hesitate to post an issue on Github. If you have comments about it, you can post a comment on this post or contact me by email.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>budgetwarrior</category><category>Gentoo</category><category>Linux</category><category>Tools</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2014/01/budgetwarrior-0-2-1-minor-changes-gentoo-ebuild.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2014 11:41:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>budgetwarrior 0.2 - Visual reports, fortune status and expenses aggregates</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2013/10/budgetwarrior-0-2-visual-reports-fortune-status-expenses-aggregates.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I've released a new version of budgetwarrior the version 0.2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've several new features to the tool. First, I've added a graph of the expenses/earnings/balances of each month for a given year in the form of a bar plot. You can see an example in practice here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://baptiste-wicht.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/Screenshot-from-2013-10-25-215839.png"&gt;&lt;img class="size-medium wp-image-2617" alt="budgetwarrior monthly report" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/Screenshot-from-2013-10-25-215839-300x266.png" width="300" height="266"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nothing fancy, but it gives a good overview of the current state of your budget.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've added a new module, called fortune, that lets you enter your total fortune and then computes the difference between the entered fortune statuses. For now, it doesn't do anything else with this data. But in the future, I want to correlate this data with the balances to check the difference between the filled expenses and earnings and the fortune evolution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've also added a more convenient way of creating expenses and earnings. Just type "budget expense add" and you'll be able to fill all the fields one by one. Of course, the command line commands are still available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last new feature I've added is an aggregate report (budget overview aggregate). This view simply groups all the expenses with the same name of a year together. If you always use the same expense title for your groceries, you'll see the total you spent in groceries for a year. You can also name your expenses with the format "Category/Expenses" and all the expenses with the same category will be grouped together in the aggregate view. That allows you to still have enough details in the monthly overview but to logically groups your expenses together in the aggregate view.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other changes are minor. I've improved the monthly overview to sort the expenses and earnings by date. To facilitate the storage of the files in a service like Dropbox, the data and configuration files are now only written if they have been modified. The mean in the current overview has been changed to reflect only the months up to the current month and not the future (which was just ruining the means).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are interested by the tool, you can download it on Github: &lt;a title="budgetwarrior repository" href="https://github.com/wichtounet/budgetwarrior"&gt;budgetwarrior&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope this tool will be useful to some people. If you've any question, just let a comment on this post or contact me directly by email. I'll be glad to help.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>budgetwarrior</category><category>C++</category><category>Others</category><category>projects</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2013/10/budgetwarrior-0-2-visual-reports-fortune-status-expenses-aggregates.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 25 Oct 2013 14:10:50 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>budgetwarrior 0.1.0 - command-line personal budgeting tool</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2013/08/budgetwarrior-command-line-personal-budgeting.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Being bored by using Google spreadsheets for my personal budgeting, I decided to write an application to do that. Being a huge fan of taskwarrior, I decided to write a kind of similar application for my personal budget, budgetwarrior was born. I use it since two months and I thought that it could be useful for other persons. The application is developed in C++. More information is available on Github: &lt;a title="https://github.com/wichtounet/budgetwarrior" href="https://github.com/wichtounet/budgetwarrior"&gt;https://github.com/wichtounet/budgetwarrior&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;budgetwarrior 0.1.0 is a command-line only tool. It works on this principle: you create a set of accounts with a certain limit and then you declare your expenses in each of these accounts. You can also manage earnings that are not each month in each account. You can also keeps track of your debts via this application. It also supports automatic creation of recurring expenses, for instance when you pay the rent (for now, only monthly expenses are supported).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you've put all your data in the application, it provides you report on the state of your budget by month or by year. For instance, here is my current monthly report:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://baptiste-wicht.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/Screenshot-from-2013-08-23-145358.png"&gt;&lt;img class="size-medium wp-image-2601" title="Monthly Report" alt="Monthly Report" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/Screenshot-from-2013-08-23-145358-300x95.png" width="300" height="95"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can see directly which accounts are in a good shape and which are not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the current yearly report:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://baptiste-wicht.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/Screenshot-from-2013-08-23-145911.png"&gt;&lt;img class="size-medium wp-image-2602" alt="Yearly report" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/Screenshot-from-2013-08-23-145911-300x252.png" width="300" height="252"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this view, you can see directly how your accounts evolve during the year and where are your biggest expenses and earnings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As everything is displayed horizontally, the more accounts you have the larger the view become. With the 7 accounts I have, it takes about 1600 pixels of width to display it. I will try to improve that in the future if some people are interested in making it work on smaller screens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Installation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can install budgetwarrior directly from the sources:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;git clone -b master git://github.com/wichtounet/budgetwarrior.git
cd budgetwarrior
cmake .
make
sudo make install&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After that, you can use budgetwarrior by using the command &lt;em&gt;budget&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The usage is fairly simple, you can use &lt;em&gt;budget help&lt;/em&gt; to have the list of the commands that you have to use to create expenses and earnings and display overviews.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;The project&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have any question on the project, don't hesitate to contact me or to post a comment to this post. If there are people interested, I can write a more complete help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have a suggestion or you found a bug, please post an issue on the github project: &lt;a title="https://github.com/wichtounet/budgetwarrior" href="https://github.com/wichtounet/budgetwarrior"&gt;https://github.com/wichtounet/budgetwarrior&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>budgetwarrior</category><category>C++</category><category>projects</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2013/08/budgetwarrior-command-line-personal-budgeting.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Aug 2013 06:41:03 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>