<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>Blog blog("Baptiste Wicht"); (Posts about Home Automation)</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/</link><description></description><atom:link rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" href="http://baptiste-wicht.com/categories/home-automation.xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 04 Jun 2017 20:17:47 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Home Automation: Power Meter and Integration of Zwave into Domoticz</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2017/04/home-automation-power-meter-integration-zwave-domoticz.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I've improved a bit my home automation installation. It's been a while since
the last upgrade, but unfortunately I cannot afford as many upgrades as I would
like :P&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a long time I wanted to monitor the power consumption of a few of my
appliances in my apartment. Especially my Linux servers so that I could try to
improve the consumption and reduce my bill on the long run. Unfortunately, there
are very few options for power meter in Switzerland due to the special type of
plug we have. The only option I found is a Zwave power plug. For a while,
I waited to see if I could find other options because Zwave devices are quite
expensive and I would have rather preferred to stay with simpler and cheaper
RF-433 appliances. Since I didn't find anything, I ordered a ZWave USB
controller from  Aeon Labs (the generation 5). I also ordered two Aeon Labs
Swiss Smart Plug with power meter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is an image of the Aeon Labs key:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Aeon Labs ZWave USB Key" class="align-center" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/zwave_usb.jpg"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And of the power meter in usage:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="ZWave power meter" class="align-center" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/power_meter.jpg"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Integration of ZWave into Domoticz was extremely easy. I just plugged the USB
key, restarted Domoticz (seems necessary for it to pick the new tty) and added
new hardware "OpenZWave USB" with the correct serial port. From there, there are
two main ways to add new devices. The first is to remove the USB key and use the
synchronization button on both the key and the device close to each other. The
other way is to use the "Include Node" option on Domoticz and then press the
synchronization button on the device to detect the new device. I used the second
option since it seemed simpler and it worked perfectly. I did that for my two
plugs and it worked fine. Directly after this, 5 new devices were added for each
of the plug. One for the voltage, one for the current , two for the  usage (I
don't know why there is two, but they are both reporting the same value) and one
for the switch on/off. I was a bit afraid that only the On/Off part of the smart
plug would work on Domoticz, but I had absolutely no problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is for instance the power usage of last 24 hours on my television system:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Power usage on television system" class="align-center" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/domoticz_power_usage.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now, I haven't integrated this information on any rule, but I plan to
monitor this information in the coming weeks and try to improve my consumption,
especially for my servers. I also plan to purchase more of these plugs once my
home automation budget can be upgraded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On another note, I also purchased a Chacon wall remote switch working in RF-433.
Although it is quite cheap, I'm very disappointed by the quality of this switch.
I add to straighten myself the pins that are attached to the battery because
there was no contact. After that, it worked correctly and it is able to work
with the RFLink module.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have to say that I'm quite satisfied with ZWave devices with this experience.
Even though I still feel it is way too expensive, it is high quality and have
a good finishing. I'll probably purchase more ZWave devices in the future. I'm
especially interested in The Aeotec 6 in 1 sensor for temperature humidity,
motion, light, UV and vibration. This would allow me to have much information in
each room with only one sensor in place of several sensors in each room like
I currently have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I still have a few Milight Bulbs and LEDS to install with a secondary Milight
bridge that I will install in the coming week, but I probably won't do a post
about this.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Domoticz</category><category>Home Automation</category><category>Personal</category><category>projects</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2017/04/home-automation-power-meter-integration-zwave-domoticz.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 23 Apr 2017 14:43:13 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Home Automation: First attempt at voice control with Jarvis</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2017/02/home-automation-first-attempt-voice-control-jarvis.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I have several devices in my home that can be controller via Domoticz, a few
power outlets, a few lights (more are coming), my Kodi home theater. And I have
a lot of sensors and information gathered by Domoticz. All of this is working
quite well, but I have only a few actuators and intelligence (motion sensor,
button and some automation via Lua script).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My next objective was to add voice control to my system. If I was living in
United States or United Kingdom I would directly an Amazon Dot or even an Amazon
Echo, but they are not available in Switzerland. I could have arranged for
delivery, but if I want my system to be useful to several people, I need to have
in French. It's the same problem with the Google Home system. So, no other way
than custom solutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since I had an extra Raspberry Pi 2, I based my system on this. I bought a Trust
Mico microphone and a Trust Compact speakers and installed them on the Pi. Both
peripherals are working quite well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can have a closer look at my microphone:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Trust Mico microphone for Jarvis Home Automation Voice Control" class="align-center" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/jarvis_mic.jpg"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and the complete installation:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Jarvis Home Automation Voice Control around my TV" class="align-center" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/jarvis_full.jpg"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Raspberry Pi is on the bottom, the speakers below the TV, left and right and
the microphone on the top right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the voice control software, I decided to go with Jarvis. It seems to me that
this is the best suited software for this kind of project. Moreover, it supports
French natively which seems good. I also tried Jasper, but this has been such
a pain to install that I gave up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jarvis is reasonably easy to install if you have a recent Raspbian image. It
took some time to install the dependencies, but in the end it was not difficult.
The installation process has a step-by-step wizard help so it's really easy to
configure everything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, even if it's easy to install, it's easy to configure correctly. The
first thing is to configure the hotword to activate commands. There are several
options, but I used snowboy which is offline and is made for hotword
recognition. This worked quite well, you just have to train a model with the
hotword to recognize the voice. After this, the problems started... You then
have to configure audio for the commands themselves. There are 6 parameters for
audio capture (noise levels to start and stop the capture, silence levels, ...)
and no help to tune them. So basically, I tried a lot of combinations until
I had something working reasonably well. When you are in debug mode, you can
listen to what the system captured. These parameters are dependent on your
environment and on your microphone and on your voice. I may be dumb but it took
several hours and a lot of tries to get a configuration working. After this, you
have to choose the engine for recognition of the commands. Unfortunately, all
the good options are online so everything you'll say as commands after the
hotword will be sent online. I first tried Bing, but I had very poor recognition
rate. I then switched to wit.ai which gave me better results. In the end, I have
about 60% recognition rate, which is not great at all, but at least some phrases
are working almost all the time while others are always failing. Another problem
I have with this is the large delay between commands and action. It takes almost
five seconds between the end of my sentence and the time where the lights in my
living room are tuned on or off by Jarvis via Domoticz.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far, I'm a bit disappointed by the quality of the system, but maybe I was
hoping for too much. I have been able to control a few of my appliances but not
really reliably. Another thing I have realized is that when counting the
Raspberry Pi, its enclosure the Microphone and the speakers, this system is more
costly than an Amazon Dot and seem highly inferior (and is much less good
looking).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll try to improve the current system with better configuration and commands in
the coming days and I will maybe try another system for voice control. I still
hope Amazon Alexa systems or Google Home are made available in
France/Switzerland not too far in the future, since I believe these systems are
a better solution than custom made systems, at least for now. Moreover, next
month, I plan to integrate ZWave into my systems with a few sensors, complete
the lighting installation and add new motion sensors. This should make it more
useful. And hopefully, by this time, I should have a good voice control system,
but I'm not too hopeful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don't hesitate to comment or contact me if you have questions about this
installation or want to share experience about voice control in home automation.
If you want more details about this, dont' hesitate to ask as well ;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Home Automation</category><category>Personal</category><category>projects</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2017/02/home-automation-first-attempt-voice-control-jarvis.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 14 Feb 2017 17:34:19 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Add Milight smart lights to my Domoticz home automation system</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2017/01/add-milight-smart-lights-to-domoticz-home-automation-system.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Recently, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2017/01/new-home-automation-system-with-domoticz.html#"&gt;I switched from my hand crafted home automation system to Domoticz&lt;/a&gt;.
This allows me to easily integrate new smart devices and remote controllable
peripherals without much effort. I plan to relate my effort in having fun
controlling my home :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm now able to control lights in two rooms with Domoticz. The most well-known
smart bulbs are the Philips Hue. However, they are stupidly expensive. There are
a lot of alternatives. I've ordered some Milight light bulbs and controller to
test with Domoticz. I didn't order a lot of them because I wanted to make sure
they would work with my system.
Milight system is working over Wifi. There are several components to a Milight
system:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The LED Light Bulbs with Red/Green/Blue/White channels&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Wifi Controller that is able to control 4 zones&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An RGBW Controller for LED strip&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first two are necessary for any installation, the third is to control an
RGBW LED strip. This list is not exhaustive, it's only the components that
I have used. It is important to note that a single Wifi controller can only
control 4 zones. There are also remotes, but I have not bought one since I plan
to use them only from Domoticz and maybe smartphone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The installation of the controller is relatively easy. You need to download the
Milight 2.0 application on the Android Play Store (or the equivalent for IOS).
Then, you can power on the Wifi Controller. It'll create a new Wifi on which you
can then connect on your phone. Then, you can use the application on your phone
to configure the device and make it connect to your home wireless network. Once,
this is done, you can connect your phone back to your home network. You can then
use the Milight application to configure your device. I highly recommend to set
a static IP address to the controller. The way I did it is simply to set a fixed
IP address on my DHCP server based on the MAC address of the MAC controller but
you can simply do the configuration in the application or in the web interface
of the controller (the user and password combination is admin:admin).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the look of the controller (next to my RFLink):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Milight wifi controller" class="align-center" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/system.jpg"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(My phone is starting to die, hence the very bad quality of images)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can then install your LED light bulbs. For, open first the remote on your
Android Milight application. Then plug the light bulb without power first. Then
power on the light and press once on one of the I buttons on one of the zones on
the remote. This will link the LED to the selected zone on the controller. You
can then control the light from your phone. Remember, only four zones and
therefore four lights per controller.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The installation for a LED strip is not much complicated. You need to plug the
4 wires (or 5 wires if your have an actual RGBW LED) into the corresponding
inputs on the controller. Then, you power it and you can link it to a zone like
a normal light bulb!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="LEDS in my Living Room controlled by Milight" class="align-center" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/leds.jpg"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It works really well and directly without problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last step is of course to configure your controller in Domoticz. It is
really easy to do. You need to add a new hardware of each of the Milight
controller. It is listed under the name "Limitless/AppLamp/Mi Light with
LAN/WiFi interface". You then can set the IP address and the port by default is
8899. Once you did configure the hardware, you'll see new devices appear in the
Devices list. There will one device for each zone and one device to control all
four zones at once. You can add the device you already configured as switches.
From the Switches interface you can turn the lamp on and off and you can&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Domoticz Light Bulbs control" class="align-center" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/domoticz_rgbw.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can then put them on your floor plan or control them from your rules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far, I'm pretty satisfied with this Milight system. The Android application
is of poor quality but aside from this is pretty good and the price is very
fair. I'm also really satisfied with the Domoticz support. The only that is sad
is that the Domoticz Android application does not support RGBW control of the
lamps, only on and off, but that is already cool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that all of this is working well, I've ordered a few more light bulbs to
cover all my rooms and a few LED controller to control (and install first) the
other LEDS that I have in mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On another note, I've also added a new outside temperature sensor outside my
apartment. It is a very cheap Chinese sensor, bought on Ebay, based on the
XT200 system that is working very well with RFLink.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next step in my system is probably to integrate Voice Control, but I don't
know exactly which way I'll go. I ordered a simple microphone that I intend to
plug on my spare Raspberry Pi, but I don't know if the range will be enough to
cover a room. Ideally, I would like to use an Amazon Dot, but they are not
available in Switzerland. I'll probably write more on the subject once I've
found an adequate solution. Another idea I've is to integrate support for ZWave
via OpenZWave and then add a few more cool sensors that I haven't found on an
cheaper system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope this is interesting and don't hesitate if you have any question about my
home automation project. You can expect a few more posts about this as soon as
In improve it :)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Home Automation</category><category>Personal</category><category>projects</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2017/01/add-milight-smart-lights-to-domoticz-home-automation-system.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 15 Jan 2017 21:00:25 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>New home automation system with Domoticz</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2017/01/new-home-automation-system-with-domoticz.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;As you may remember, I started going into Home Automation last year with a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2016/08/asgard-home-automation-project.html"&gt;C++ project, Asgard&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I haven't add the time to improve this project further and make
it really useful and I have so many C++ projects already, so I decided to switch
to using an existing project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="choice"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Choice&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I needed a system that was at least able to handle everything my existing system
does:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Control my RF-433 Temperature Sensors (Oregon Temperature Sensors)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Control my RF-433 Remote Button&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Control my smart power outlets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ping and wake-on-lan my different computers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be installable on a Raspberry Pi&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Control Skadi/Kodi Home Cinema&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, it also had to be open source and in a language that I can write
without agonizing pain (no Ruby, no JavaScript, ideally no Python (I hate a lot
of languages...)).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's impressive the number of home automation projects that exist today. It's
really a hot topic, more than I though. After a few hours of research, I've
finally settled on Domoticz. It seemed that it could handle all my home
automation devices that I already had. Domoticz is an open source home
automation system. It's written mainly in C++, which is an advantage for me
since I'll be able to work inside it if necessary. It has a quite modern HTML5
interface. It has a lot of support for hardware and a lot of bridges for other
controllers as well. One of the reason I chose it is also the floor-planner
feature that looks really cool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="installation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Installation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, I cleaned the hardware of my Raspberry Pi. I got rid of my
breadboard and the components on it. Then, I put the Raspberry Pi on a nicer box
that I had laying around. One problem with Domoticz is that it does not support
directly RF433 devices, but need a controller in the middle. At first,
I believed I could simply connect them through GPIO and lets Domoticz do the
rest, but it's not possible. I ordered the different pieces for a RFLink
controller at nodo-shops. It is running on a Arduino Mega and is connected to
the Pi. The very big advantage is that they handle a lot of protocols directly,
so you only have to read the serial port to get information on RF-433 events.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is how the current system look:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Asgard automation system hardware" class="align-center" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/home_automation_hardware.jpg"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The black box is the Arduino Mega with RFLink software while the Transparent is
simply the Raspberry on which Domoticz is installed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for the installation of Domoticz, it's really simple. They also have images of
Raspberry Pi directly, but since my Raspberry was already installed with
Raspbian, I installed Domoticz on it directly. A simple matter of curl and bash:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code bash"&gt;&lt;a name="rest_code_2f18ad65bc734bb0940e74ca0a51ffb5-1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;sudo curl -L install.domoticz.com &lt;span class="p"&gt;|&lt;/span&gt; sudo bash
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;After a few questions, your installation should be complete. You can browse your
Domoticz installation at the IP of your Pi and at the given port.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="home-automation-with-domoticz"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Home Automation with Domoticz&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are several concepts in Domoticz that are important. At first, it seemed
a bit weird to me, but in the end it works really well and you get used to it
pretty fast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first concept is the hardware. It is not necessary hardware directly, but
rather a driver to some piece of information of switches than a real hardware in
my opinion. For instance, the RFLink Gateway is considered hardware as well as
the Forecast weather API. Here is all the hardware I've configured:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Domoticz Hardware Configuration" class="align-center" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/domoticz_hardware.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've got some sensors from the motherboard, the Kodi interaction, the driver to
ping the different computers, the Forecast weather with Dark Sky and Weather
Underground, the RFLink communication, the wake-on-lan and some dummies virtual
switches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On its own, an hardware is useless, but it can create devices that will be used
for home automation. A device is sub device of a particular driver. In some
cases, the devices will be created automatically. For instance, RF Link can
create devices as soon as they are detected. For wake-on-lan, you have to
configure MAC Addresses and they will be added as devices. And so on...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a lot of types of devices, also called switches. Some devices can do
some actions, for instance the wake-on-lan devices, while others are information
based such as ping or temperature sensors detected from the RFLink. For
instance, here are my temperature sensors:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Domoticz Temperature Sensors" class="align-center" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/domoticz_temperature.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for my hardware I already had, I haven't add too many issues with them. The
Oregon Temperature Sensors worked out of the box without any issues as well my
old RF433 Ninja Block temperature sensor. The smart power outlets have been
pretty easy to use as well. The most problem I've add was with the remote
buttons. It seems to many that it should be the easiest, but RFLink has a lot of
problem with them, they are detected several times and are highly unreliable.
Interestingly you can also change the icon of most device to a large variety of
existing devices so that they would look more realistic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another feature I find pretty cool is the floor plan. You can create plans for
each floor of your house and then create rooms inside and finally attach devices
to each room and place inside the plan. Unfortunately, to draw the plan, you'll
have to use an external tool. I've used floorplanner for this, but you may use
any plan you have as long as you have an image.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is my floor plan with the devices (the scale is terribly off :P) :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Domoticz Floor Plan" class="align-center" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/domoticz_floorplan.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that you can directly see the status of each of your sensors in each room.
Moreover, you can also activate some devices directly from the floor plan as
well :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Normally, my Somfy blinds are supposed to work with the RFLink controller.
I have managed to control my blinds but only when the RFLink was within 50
centimeters of the Blinds, which is clearly not acceptable. I don't know from
where the problem comes. It may come from my Blinds controller inside the wall
or may come from bad antenna of the RFLink or from a bug in RFLink, so from now
I cannot control my blinds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have several D-Link cameras at home. You can also add cameras to Domoticz, but
don't expect a lot of support on this side. It's pretty poor indeed. The only
useful you can do in Domoticz with Cameras is to take a screenshot from them.
You cannot control the Camera or even have a decent video stream and cannot do
motion detection directly. I hope that the Camera support will improve in the
future. One thing that would be good is to add a view of the cameras in the
floor plan, but it is not possible currently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I did is to use Zoneminder to manage the cameras and send alert to Domoticz
when motion is detect with the REST API of Domoticz. Unfortunately that means
two systems to manage the Cameras. Zoneminder is a very good piece of software,
but one of the ugliest I've ever seen (even I can do a better web interface...)
and quite obscure to configure. But the numbers of cameras it can handle and the
capabilities to control the camera is very very powerful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="events-and-actions"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Events and actions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No home automation system would be complete without an events and rules system.
In Domoticz, you have several ways to create rules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first solution is to create group. A group is simply a set of switches that
are all activated together. This is pretty limited, but can be useful. The
second solution is a scene. A scene is activated by a device and can set several
switches to on or off after the activation. The problem with this is that you
have to listen for an action as activation, you cannot use an existing device or
a rule with a value. For me, these two possibilities are way too limited and
I don't really a reason to use them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best solution is to script an handler. For that, there are two ways, either
you define visually your script with blocky, for instance:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Domoticz Blockly Rule" class="align-center" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/domoticz_blockly.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This seemed so cool that I wanted to do all my rules with that. Unfortunately,
it is really limited. The main limitation is that you cannot nest if blocks. In
fact the interface lets you do, but it doesn't work afterwards. The other
limitation is that it has no notion of time. For instance, it's very hard to
create an action if a computer is shutdown for more than 60 seconds. You can do
it, but you end up creating virtual devices which are turned off after some
delay and it gets really complicated really soon...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, I used Lua script directly. These scripts have the information about
the last values of each device and the last updated time as well. It's much
easier with that to create powerful rules especially when you want a notion of
time. There are plenty of examples on the Domoticz forum about very powerful
rules that you can create. Unfortunately, there are some limitations. For
instance, you cannot send several actions to the same device in the same script
Moreover, you also have to decode the values of the sensors yourself. For
instance, for a temperature and humidity sensor, you'll have to parse the values
and extract the one you need by hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far, I haven't created many rules, only four. The first rule is that with the
push of one remote button I can power on my smart socket and turn on one of my
computers in my office. Then, if both the computers on this smart sockets have
been off for more than 60 seconds, the power is shut off on the smart socket.
And I have done almost the same for my media center and TV in my living room.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the future, I'll probably only use the Lua scripting capability. In my
opinion, it's better to have all the scripts in the same language for
maintainability reasons. Once my futures devices arrive, I'll have a few more
rules to code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="conclusion"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To wrap up, I'd say that I'm pretty satisfied with my new home automation system
with Domoticz. It's not a perfect tool, but it has a lot of features and is
working quite well in general. I would recommend you to try it if you want
a good home automation system, fully featured and relatively easy to use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've several more things planned for this system. I plan to test a real motion
sensor rather than rely only on the cameras which are focused on the doors and
windows. I also plan to add an outdoor temperature sensor. And more
interestingly, I'm going to try to integrate smart bulbs from Milight to be able
to control my lights from the system. These are the shot term projects that
I want to do, but I have many more ideas!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm also sure that there are some features from Domoticz that I have overlooked
or not discovered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll probably write more posts on Home Automation on the coming months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more information on Domoticz, you can consult
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://domoticz.com/"&gt;the official Domoticz website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Home Automation</category><category>Personal</category><category>projects</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2017/01/new-home-automation-system-with-domoticz.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 08 Jan 2017 15:08:42 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Asgard: Home Automation project</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2016/08/asgard-home-automation-project.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I have updated my asgard project to make it finally useful for me, so I figured
I'd present the project now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Asgard is my project of home automation based on a Raspberry Pi. I started this
project after Ninja Blocks kickstarter company went down and I was left with
useless sensors. So I figured why not have fun creating my own :P I know there
are some other projects out there that are pretty good, but I wanted to do some
more low level stuff for once, so what the hell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, everything is written in C++, no surprise here. The project is built
upon a server / drivers architecture. The drivers and the server are talking via
network sockets, so they can be on different machines.  The server is displaying
the data it got on a web interface and also provide a way to trigger actions of
drivers either from the web interface or through the integrated rules engine.
The data are stored in a database, accessed with CPPSqlite3 (probably going to
be replaced by sqlcpp11) and the web server is handled with mongoose (with a c++
interface).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I must mention that most of the web part of the project was made by a student of
mine, Stéphane Ly, who work on it as part of his study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a picture of the Raspberry Pi system (not very pretty ;) ):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Asgard automation system hardware" class="align-center" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/asgard_hardware.jpg"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I plan to try to fit at least some of it on a nicer box with nicer cables and
such. Moreover, I also plan to add real antennas to the RF transmitter and
receiver, but I haven't received them so far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="sensors"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Sensors&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;asgard support several sensors:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;DHT11 Temperature/Humdity Sensor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;WT450 Temperature/Humdity Sensor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;RF Button&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;IR Remote&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CPU Temperature Sensor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can see the sensors data displayed on the web interface:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Asgard automation system home page" class="align-center" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/asgard_home.png"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="actions"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are currently a few actions provided by the drivers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wake-On-Lan a computer by its MAC Address&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ITT-1500 smart plugs ON and OFF&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kodi actions: Pause / Play / Next / Previous on Kodi&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are the rules engine:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Asgard automation system rules page" class="align-center" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/asgard_rules.png"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="my-home-automation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;My home automation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm currently using this system to monitor the temperature in my appartment.
Nothing great so far because I don't have enough sensors yet. And now, I'm also
using a wireless button to turn on my power socket, wait 2 seconds and then
power on my Kodi Home Theater with wake on lan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's nothing fancy so far, but it's already better than what I had with Ninja
Blocks, except for the ugly hardware ;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="future"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Future&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are still tons of work on the project and on integration in my home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I'm really dissatisfied with the WT450 sensor, I've ordered new Oregon sensors to try to do better.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I've ordered a few new sensors: Door intrusion detector and motion detector&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The rules system needs to be improve to support multiple conditions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I plan to add a simple state system to the asgard server&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are a lot of refactorings necessary in the code and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, I don't know when I'll work on this again, my work on this project is
pretty episodic to say the least.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="code"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Code&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The code is, as always, available on Github. There are multiple repositories:
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/search?q=user%3Awichtounet+asgard"&gt;all asgard repositories&lt;/a&gt;.
It's not that much code for now, about 2000 lines of code, but some of it may be
useful. If you plan to use the system, keep in mind that it was never tested out
of my environment and that there is no documentation so far, but don't hesitate
to open Issues on Github if you have questions or post a comment here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>asgard</category><category>Home Automation</category><category>Personal</category><category>projects</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2016/08/asgard-home-automation-project.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 27 Aug 2016 20:28:16 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>