<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>Blog blog("Baptiste Wicht"); (Posts about Personal)</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/</link><description></description><atom:link type="application/rss+xml" rel="self" href="http://baptiste-wicht.com/categories/personal.xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 17 Oct 2017 18:58:43 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>I successfully defended my Ph.D.</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2017/10/i-successfully-defended-my-phd.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I'm happy to announce that I've successfully defended my thesis "Deep Learning
Features for Image Processing". After four years, I've defended it officially in
front of the thesis committed last Friday and then again two days ago I've
successfully publicly defended in front of my friends, family and colleagues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm now a "Doctor of Philosophy in Computer Science :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will update my thesis with the last comments in November and send the final
version to the university. At which point, I'll publish it on this website as
well.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Machine Learning</category><category>Personal</category><category>thesis</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2017/10/i-successfully-defended-my-phd.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 15 Oct 2017 15:16:29 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Home Automation: Power Meter and Integration of Zwave into Domoticz</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2017/04/home-automation-power-meter-integration-zwave-domoticz.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I've improved a bit my home automation installation. It's been a while since
the last upgrade, but unfortunately I cannot afford as many upgrades as I would
like :P&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a long time I wanted to monitor the power consumption of a few of my
appliances in my apartment. Especially my Linux servers so that I could try to
improve the consumption and reduce my bill on the long run. Unfortunately, there
are very few options for power meter in Switzerland due to the special type of
plug we have. The only option I found is a Zwave power plug. For a while,
I waited to see if I could find other options because Zwave devices are quite
expensive and I would have rather preferred to stay with simpler and cheaper
RF-433 appliances. Since I didn't find anything, I ordered a ZWave USB
controller from  Aeon Labs (the generation 5). I also ordered two Aeon Labs
Swiss Smart Plug with power meter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is an image of the Aeon Labs key:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Aeon Labs ZWave USB Key" class="align-center" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/zwave_usb.jpg"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And of the power meter in usage:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="ZWave power meter" class="align-center" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/power_meter.jpg"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Integration of ZWave into Domoticz was extremely easy. I just plugged the USB
key, restarted Domoticz (seems necessary for it to pick the new tty) and added
new hardware "OpenZWave USB" with the correct serial port. From there, there are
two main ways to add new devices. The first is to remove the USB key and use the
synchronization button on both the key and the device close to each other. The
other way is to use the "Include Node" option on Domoticz and then press the
synchronization button on the device to detect the new device. I used the second
option since it seemed simpler and it worked perfectly. I did that for my two
plugs and it worked fine. Directly after this, 5 new devices were added for each
of the plug. One for the voltage, one for the current , two for the  usage (I
don't know why there is two, but they are both reporting the same value) and one
for the switch on/off. I was a bit afraid that only the On/Off part of the smart
plug would work on Domoticz, but I had absolutely no problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is for instance the power usage of last 24 hours on my television system:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Power usage on television system" class="align-center" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/domoticz_power_usage.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now, I haven't integrated this information on any rule, but I plan to
monitor this information in the coming weeks and try to improve my consumption,
especially for my servers. I also plan to purchase more of these plugs once my
home automation budget can be upgraded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On another note, I also purchased a Chacon wall remote switch working in RF-433.
Although it is quite cheap, I'm very disappointed by the quality of this switch.
I add to straighten myself the pins that are attached to the battery because
there was no contact. After that, it worked correctly and it is able to work
with the RFLink module.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have to say that I'm quite satisfied with ZWave devices with this experience.
Even though I still feel it is way too expensive, it is high quality and have
a good finishing. I'll probably purchase more ZWave devices in the future. I'm
especially interested in The Aeotec 6 in 1 sensor for temperature humidity,
motion, light, UV and vibration. This would allow me to have much information in
each room with only one sensor in place of several sensors in each room like
I currently have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I still have a few Milight Bulbs and LEDS to install with a secondary Milight
bridge that I will install in the coming week, but I probably won't do a post
about this.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Domoticz</category><category>Home Automation</category><category>Personal</category><category>projects</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2017/04/home-automation-power-meter-integration-zwave-domoticz.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 23 Apr 2017 14:43:13 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Home Automation: First attempt at voice control with Jarvis</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2017/02/home-automation-first-attempt-voice-control-jarvis.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I have several devices in my home that can be controller via Domoticz, a few
power outlets, a few lights (more are coming), my Kodi home theater. And I have
a lot of sensors and information gathered by Domoticz. All of this is working
quite well, but I have only a few actuators and intelligence (motion sensor,
button and some automation via Lua script).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My next objective was to add voice control to my system. If I was living in
United States or United Kingdom I would directly an Amazon Dot or even an Amazon
Echo, but they are not available in Switzerland. I could have arranged for
delivery, but if I want my system to be useful to several people, I need to have
in French. It's the same problem with the Google Home system. So, no other way
than custom solutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since I had an extra Raspberry Pi 2, I based my system on this. I bought a Trust
Mico microphone and a Trust Compact speakers and installed them on the Pi. Both
peripherals are working quite well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can have a closer look at my microphone:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Trust Mico microphone for Jarvis Home Automation Voice Control" class="align-center" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/jarvis_mic.jpg"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and the complete installation:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Jarvis Home Automation Voice Control around my TV" class="align-center" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/jarvis_full.jpg"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Raspberry Pi is on the bottom, the speakers below the TV, left and right and
the microphone on the top right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the voice control software, I decided to go with Jarvis. It seems to me that
this is the best suited software for this kind of project. Moreover, it supports
French natively which seems good. I also tried Jasper, but this has been such
a pain to install that I gave up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jarvis is reasonably easy to install if you have a recent Raspbian image. It
took some time to install the dependencies, but in the end it was not difficult.
The installation process has a step-by-step wizard help so it's really easy to
configure everything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, even if it's easy to install, it's easy to configure correctly. The
first thing is to configure the hotword to activate commands. There are several
options, but I used snowboy which is offline and is made for hotword
recognition. This worked quite well, you just have to train a model with the
hotword to recognize the voice. After this, the problems started... You then
have to configure audio for the commands themselves. There are 6 parameters for
audio capture (noise levels to start and stop the capture, silence levels, ...)
and no help to tune them. So basically, I tried a lot of combinations until
I had something working reasonably well. When you are in debug mode, you can
listen to what the system captured. These parameters are dependent on your
environment and on your microphone and on your voice. I may be dumb but it took
several hours and a lot of tries to get a configuration working. After this, you
have to choose the engine for recognition of the commands. Unfortunately, all
the good options are online so everything you'll say as commands after the
hotword will be sent online. I first tried Bing, but I had very poor recognition
rate. I then switched to wit.ai which gave me better results. In the end, I have
about 60% recognition rate, which is not great at all, but at least some phrases
are working almost all the time while others are always failing. Another problem
I have with this is the large delay between commands and action. It takes almost
five seconds between the end of my sentence and the time where the lights in my
living room are tuned on or off by Jarvis via Domoticz.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far, I'm a bit disappointed by the quality of the system, but maybe I was
hoping for too much. I have been able to control a few of my appliances but not
really reliably. Another thing I have realized is that when counting the
Raspberry Pi, its enclosure the Microphone and the speakers, this system is more
costly than an Amazon Dot and seem highly inferior (and is much less good
looking).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll try to improve the current system with better configuration and commands in
the coming days and I will maybe try another system for voice control. I still
hope Amazon Alexa systems or Google Home are made available in
France/Switzerland not too far in the future, since I believe these systems are
a better solution than custom made systems, at least for now. Moreover, next
month, I plan to integrate ZWave into my systems with a few sensors, complete
the lighting installation and add new motion sensors. This should make it more
useful. And hopefully, by this time, I should have a good voice control system,
but I'm not too hopeful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don't hesitate to comment or contact me if you have questions about this
installation or want to share experience about voice control in home automation.
If you want more details about this, dont' hesitate to ask as well ;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Home Automation</category><category>Personal</category><category>projects</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2017/02/home-automation-first-attempt-voice-control-jarvis.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 14 Feb 2017 17:34:19 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Publications - Sudoku Recognition with Deep Belief Network</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2017/01/publications-sudoku-recognition-with-deep-belief-network.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I recently realized that I never talked about my publications on this website...
I thought it was time to start. I'll start to write a few posts about my earlier
publications and then I'll try to write something for the new ones not too late.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the story, I'm currently a PHD student at the University of Fribourg, in
Switzerland. My PHD is about the use of Deep Learning technologies to
automatically extract features from images. I have developed my Deep Learning
Library (DLL) project for this thesis. We have published a few articles on the
various projects that we tackled during the thesis. I'll try to go in order.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the beginning of the thesis, I used Restricted Boltzmann Machine and Deep
Belief Network to perform digit recognition on images of Sudoku taken with
a phone camera. We published two papers on this subject.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/282303748_Camera-based_Sudoku_recognition_with_deep_belief_network"&gt;Camera-based Sudoku Recognition with Deep Belief Network&lt;/a&gt;, in the Proceedings of the International Conference on Soft Computing and Pattern Recognition (SOCPAR-2014)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/307545305_Mixed_handwritten_and_printed_digit_recognition_in_Sudoku_with_Convolutional_Deep_Belief_Network"&gt;Mixed Handwritten and printed digit recognition in Sudoku With Convolutional Deep Belief Network&lt;/a&gt;, in the Proceedings of the International Conference on Document Analysis and Recognition (ICDAR-2015)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Sudoku grid and digits are detected using standard image processing
techniques:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The image is first converted to grayscale, then a median blur is applied to
remove noise and the image is binarized using Adapteive Thresholding&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The edges are detected using the Canny algorithm. From these, the lines are
detected using a Progressive Probabilistic Hough Transform&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using a connected component analysis, the segments of lines are clustered
together to detect the Sudoku Grid&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The cells are then detected inside the grid using the inner lines and contour
detection is used to isolate the digits.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is one of the original images from our dataset:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Original image from our dataset" class="align-center" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/image124.jpg"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are the detected characters from the previous image:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Detected digits from our application" class="align-center" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/image124_char.jpg"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once all the digits have been found they are passed to a Deep Belief Network for
recognition. A Deep Belief Network is composed of several Restricted Boltzmann
Machines (RBM) that are stacked. The network is pretrained, by training each
RBM, in turn, with Contrastive Divergence. This algorithm basically trains each
RBM as an auto-encoder and learns a good feature representation of the inputs.
Once all the layers have been trained, the network can then be trained as
a regular neural network with Stochastic Gradient Descent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the second paper, the images of Sudoku are containing both computer printed
and handwritten digits (the grid is already filled). The other difference is
that the second system used a Convolutional DBN instead of DBN. The difference
being that each layer is a Convolutional RBM. Such a model will learn a set of
small filters that will be applied to each position of the image.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the second version of the dataset, we have been able to achieve 99.14% of
recognition of the digits or 92.5% of fully-recognized grid  with the
Convolutional Network.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/wichtounet/sudoku_recognizer"&gt;C++ implementation on Github&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to have a look, I've updated the
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://baptiste-wicht.com/stories/publications.html"&gt;list of my publications&lt;/a&gt;
on this website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want more details on this project, don't hesitate to ask here or on
Github, or read the paper :)
The next post about my publications will probably be about CPU performances!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>deep learning</category><category>dll</category><category>Personal</category><category>publications</category><category>thesis</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2017/01/publications-sudoku-recognition-with-deep-belief-network.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 20 Jan 2017 07:56:46 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Add Milight smart lights to my Domoticz home automation system</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2017/01/add-milight-smart-lights-to-domoticz-home-automation-system.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Recently, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2017/01/new-home-automation-system-with-domoticz.html#"&gt;I switched from my hand crafted home automation system to Domoticz&lt;/a&gt;.
This allows me to easily integrate new smart devices and remote controllable
peripherals without much effort. I plan to relate my effort in having fun
controlling my home :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm now able to control lights in two rooms with Domoticz. The most well-known
smart bulbs are the Philips Hue. However, they are stupidly expensive. There are
a lot of alternatives. I've ordered some Milight light bulbs and controller to
test with Domoticz. I didn't order a lot of them because I wanted to make sure
they would work with my system.
Milight system is working over Wifi. There are several components to a Milight
system:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The LED Light Bulbs with Red/Green/Blue/White channels&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Wifi Controller that is able to control 4 zones&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An RGBW Controller for LED strip&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first two are necessary for any installation, the third is to control an
RGBW LED strip. This list is not exhaustive, it's only the components that
I have used. It is important to note that a single Wifi controller can only
control 4 zones. There are also remotes, but I have not bought one since I plan
to use them only from Domoticz and maybe smartphone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The installation of the controller is relatively easy. You need to download the
Milight 2.0 application on the Android Play Store (or the equivalent for IOS).
Then, you can power on the Wifi Controller. It'll create a new Wifi on which you
can then connect on your phone. Then, you can use the application on your phone
to configure the device and make it connect to your home wireless network. Once,
this is done, you can connect your phone back to your home network. You can then
use the Milight application to configure your device. I highly recommend to set
a static IP address to the controller. The way I did it is simply to set a fixed
IP address on my DHCP server based on the MAC address of the MAC controller but
you can simply do the configuration in the application or in the web interface
of the controller (the user and password combination is admin:admin).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the look of the controller (next to my RFLink):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Milight wifi controller" class="align-center" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/system.jpg"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(My phone is starting to die, hence the very bad quality of images)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can then install your LED light bulbs. For, open first the remote on your
Android Milight application. Then plug the light bulb without power first. Then
power on the light and press once on one of the I buttons on one of the zones on
the remote. This will link the LED to the selected zone on the controller. You
can then control the light from your phone. Remember, only four zones and
therefore four lights per controller.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The installation for a LED strip is not much complicated. You need to plug the
4 wires (or 5 wires if your have an actual RGBW LED) into the corresponding
inputs on the controller. Then, you power it and you can link it to a zone like
a normal light bulb!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="LEDS in my Living Room controlled by Milight" class="align-center" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/leds.jpg"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It works really well and directly without problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last step is of course to configure your controller in Domoticz. It is
really easy to do. You need to add a new hardware of each of the Milight
controller. It is listed under the name "Limitless/AppLamp/Mi Light with
LAN/WiFi interface". You then can set the IP address and the port by default is
8899. Once you did configure the hardware, you'll see new devices appear in the
Devices list. There will one device for each zone and one device to control all
four zones at once. You can add the device you already configured as switches.
From the Switches interface you can turn the lamp on and off and you can&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Domoticz Light Bulbs control" class="align-center" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/domoticz_rgbw.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can then put them on your floor plan or control them from your rules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far, I'm pretty satisfied with this Milight system. The Android application
is of poor quality but aside from this is pretty good and the price is very
fair. I'm also really satisfied with the Domoticz support. The only that is sad
is that the Domoticz Android application does not support RGBW control of the
lamps, only on and off, but that is already cool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that all of this is working well, I've ordered a few more light bulbs to
cover all my rooms and a few LED controller to control (and install first) the
other LEDS that I have in mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On another note, I've also added a new outside temperature sensor outside my
apartment. It is a very cheap Chinese sensor, bought on Ebay, based on the
XT200 system that is working very well with RFLink.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next step in my system is probably to integrate Voice Control, but I don't
know exactly which way I'll go. I ordered a simple microphone that I intend to
plug on my spare Raspberry Pi, but I don't know if the range will be enough to
cover a room. Ideally, I would like to use an Amazon Dot, but they are not
available in Switzerland. I'll probably write more on the subject once I've
found an adequate solution. Another idea I've is to integrate support for ZWave
via OpenZWave and then add a few more cool sensors that I haven't found on an
cheaper system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope this is interesting and don't hesitate if you have any question about my
home automation project. You can expect a few more posts about this as soon as
In improve it :)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Home Automation</category><category>Personal</category><category>projects</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2017/01/add-milight-smart-lights-to-domoticz-home-automation-system.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 15 Jan 2017 21:00:25 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Vivaldi + Vimium = Finally no more Firefox!</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2017/01/vivaldi-vimium-finally-no-more-firefox.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I've been using the Pentadactyl Firefox extension for a long time. This
extensions "vimifies" Firefox and it does a very good job of it. This is
probably the best extension I have ever seen on any browser. This post is really
not against Pentadactyl, this is a great addon and it still works great.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, I have been more and more dissatisfied of Mozilla Firefox over the
years. Indeed, the browser is becoming slower and slower all the time and I'm
experiencing more and more issues on Gentoo with it. But the biggest problem
I've with Firefox right now is the philosophy of the developers that is really
crappy. Currently, there is only one thing that is good in Firefox compared to
the other browsers, its extensions. Basically, an extension in Firefox can do
almost anything. Pentadactyl is able to transform most of the interface and get
rid of all of the useless parts of the interface. It is currently impossible to
do so in other browsers. These powerful addons are using the XUL/XPCOM
programming interface to do so. Pentadactyl is the only reason I've kept to
Firefox so long. But Firefox has announced, already more than a year ago, that
it will deprecate its XUL/XPCOM interface in favour of webextensions. This means
that a lot of very good addons will not be able to work anymore once the
deprecation has been completed. Several writers of popular Firefox have
announced that they will not even try to port their addons and some addons will
simply not be possible anymore. This is the case for Pentadactyl which is on the
line for when the deprecation occurs. The data for deprecated has already been
delayed but is likely to come anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For several months, I've been looking at several possible replacements for my
current Pentadactyl browser. I've tried qutebrowser, but it is really too
limited in terms of features so far. I've also tried again Chromium which is
a great browser but unfortunately, there are very few possibilities for addons
to modify the interface. Vimium is a great addon for Chromium which is basically
the very much more lightweight alternative to Pentadactyl. It has much less
features, but most of the missing features are simply things that cannot be done
in Chromium.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only recently did I test Vivaldi. Vivaldi is a free multi-platform browser,
based on Chromium and supporting Chromium extensions. The major difference with
Chrome is how the UI is customizable, due to the use of a dynamic UI, stylable
with CSS. With the customizability of Vivaldi plus the great shortcuts and
vim-like behaviour of vimium, I really feel like I found a new Pentadactyl with
the advantage of not having to bear Firefox!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is how it is looking with the follow URLs feature from vimium:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="View of my Vivaldi browser" class="align-center" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/vivaldi.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: The gray bar on the left is the console to the left and the top kind of
bar is awesome wm, they are not part of the browser.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm using the dark theme with native windows. I've disabled the address bar,
moved the tab bar to the bottom and completely hidden the side panel. All that
remained was the title bar and the scroll bar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To get rid of the title bar, you can use CSS. First, you have to only display
the Vivaldi button in the settings page. Then, you can use this custom CSS:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code CSS"&gt;&lt;a name="rest_code_186fe8fab81a4aaa8c065de05d9d0460-1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;button&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nc"&gt;vivaldi&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name="rest_code_186fe8fab81a4aaa8c065de05d9d0460-2"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;    &lt;span class="k"&gt;display&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kc"&gt;none&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="cp"&gt;!important&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name="rest_code_186fe8fab81a4aaa8c065de05d9d0460-3"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name="rest_code_186fe8fab81a4aaa8c065de05d9d0460-4"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a name="rest_code_186fe8fab81a4aaa8c065de05d9d0460-5"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;#&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nn"&gt;header&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name="rest_code_186fe8fab81a4aaa8c065de05d9d0460-6"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;    &lt;span class="k"&gt;min-height&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="cp"&gt;!important&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name="rest_code_186fe8fab81a4aaa8c065de05d9d0460-7"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;    &lt;span class="k"&gt;z-index&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kc"&gt;auto&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="cp"&gt;!important&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name="rest_code_186fe8fab81a4aaa8c065de05d9d0460-8"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name="rest_code_186fe8fab81a4aaa8c065de05d9d0460-9"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a name="rest_code_186fe8fab81a4aaa8c065de05d9d0460-10"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nc"&gt;button-toolbar&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nc"&gt;home&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;display&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kc"&gt;none&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;to hide the title completely! To get rid of the scroll bar, you need to use the
Stylish extension and use this custom CSS:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code CSS"&gt;&lt;a name="rest_code_0aba56aec8ab462280770f308f7c6469-1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nd"&gt;-webkit-scrollbar&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;display&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kc"&gt;none&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="cp"&gt;!important&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;width&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kt"&gt;px&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name="rest_code_0aba56aec8ab462280770f308f7c6469-2"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nd"&gt;-webkit-scrollbar-button&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nd"&gt;-webkit-scrollbar-track&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;display&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kc"&gt;none&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="cp"&gt;!important&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name="rest_code_0aba56aec8ab462280770f308f7c6469-3"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nd"&gt;-webkit-scrollbar-thumb&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;display&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kc"&gt;none&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="cp"&gt;!important&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name="rest_code_0aba56aec8ab462280770f308f7c6469-4"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nd"&gt;-webkit-scrollbar-track&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;display&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kc"&gt;none&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="cp"&gt;!important&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;And then, no more scroll bar :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to have full HTML5 video support, you need to install extra codecs.
On Gentoo, I've uploaded a ebuild on my overlay (wichtounet on layman) with the
name vivaldi-ffmpeg-codecs and everything should be working fine :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vimium is clearly inferior to Pentadactyl in that for instance it only works in
web page, not in system page and you still have to use the browser for a few
things, but it does not seem too bar so far. Moreover, I wasn't using all the
features of Pentadactyl. I haven't been used this browser for a long time, so
maybe there are things that I will miss from Pentadactyl, but I won't certainly
miss Firefox!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Gentoo</category><category>Google</category><category>Personal</category><category>Web</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2017/01/vivaldi-vimium-finally-no-more-firefox.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 14 Jan 2017 19:55:26 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>New home automation system with Domoticz</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2017/01/new-home-automation-system-with-domoticz.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;As you may remember, I started going into Home Automation last year with a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2016/08/asgard-home-automation-project.html"&gt;C++ project, Asgard&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I haven't add the time to improve this project further and make
it really useful and I have so many C++ projects already, so I decided to switch
to using an existing project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="choice"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Choice&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I needed a system that was at least able to handle everything my existing system
does:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Control my RF-433 Temperature Sensors (Oregon Temperature Sensors)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Control my RF-433 Remote Button&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Control my smart power outlets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ping and wake-on-lan my different computers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be installable on a Raspberry Pi&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Control Skadi/Kodi Home Cinema&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, it also had to be open source and in a language that I can write
without agonizing pain (no Ruby, no JavaScript, ideally no Python (I hate a lot
of languages...)).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's impressive the number of home automation projects that exist today. It's
really a hot topic, more than I though. After a few hours of research, I've
finally settled on Domoticz. It seemed that it could handle all my home
automation devices that I already had. Domoticz is an open source home
automation system. It's written mainly in C++, which is an advantage for me
since I'll be able to work inside it if necessary. It has a quite modern HTML5
interface. It has a lot of support for hardware and a lot of bridges for other
controllers as well. One of the reason I chose it is also the floor-planner
feature that looks really cool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="installation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Installation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, I cleaned the hardware of my Raspberry Pi. I got rid of my
breadboard and the components on it. Then, I put the Raspberry Pi on a nicer box
that I had laying around. One problem with Domoticz is that it does not support
directly RF433 devices, but need a controller in the middle. At first,
I believed I could simply connect them through GPIO and lets Domoticz do the
rest, but it's not possible. I ordered the different pieces for a RFLink
controller at nodo-shops. It is running on a Arduino Mega and is connected to
the Pi. The very big advantage is that they handle a lot of protocols directly,
so you only have to read the serial port to get information on RF-433 events.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is how the current system look:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Asgard automation system hardware" class="align-center" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/home_automation_hardware.jpg"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The black box is the Arduino Mega with RFLink software while the Transparent is
simply the Raspberry on which Domoticz is installed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for the installation of Domoticz, it's really simple. They also have images of
Raspberry Pi directly, but since my Raspberry was already installed with
Raspbian, I installed Domoticz on it directly. A simple matter of curl and bash:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code bash"&gt;&lt;a name="rest_code_2f18ad65bc734bb0940e74ca0a51ffb5-1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;sudo curl -L install.domoticz.com &lt;span class="p"&gt;|&lt;/span&gt; sudo bash
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;After a few questions, your installation should be complete. You can browse your
Domoticz installation at the IP of your Pi and at the given port.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="home-automation-with-domoticz"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Home Automation with Domoticz&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are several concepts in Domoticz that are important. At first, it seemed
a bit weird to me, but in the end it works really well and you get used to it
pretty fast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first concept is the hardware. It is not necessary hardware directly, but
rather a driver to some piece of information of switches than a real hardware in
my opinion. For instance, the RFLink Gateway is considered hardware as well as
the Forecast weather API. Here is all the hardware I've configured:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Domoticz Hardware Configuration" class="align-center" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/domoticz_hardware.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've got some sensors from the motherboard, the Kodi interaction, the driver to
ping the different computers, the Forecast weather with Dark Sky and Weather
Underground, the RFLink communication, the wake-on-lan and some dummies virtual
switches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On its own, an hardware is useless, but it can create devices that will be used
for home automation. A device is sub device of a particular driver. In some
cases, the devices will be created automatically. For instance, RF Link can
create devices as soon as they are detected. For wake-on-lan, you have to
configure MAC Addresses and they will be added as devices. And so on...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a lot of types of devices, also called switches. Some devices can do
some actions, for instance the wake-on-lan devices, while others are information
based such as ping or temperature sensors detected from the RFLink. For
instance, here are my temperature sensors:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Domoticz Temperature Sensors" class="align-center" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/domoticz_temperature.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for my hardware I already had, I haven't add too many issues with them. The
Oregon Temperature Sensors worked out of the box without any issues as well my
old RF433 Ninja Block temperature sensor. The smart power outlets have been
pretty easy to use as well. The most problem I've add was with the remote
buttons. It seems to many that it should be the easiest, but RFLink has a lot of
problem with them, they are detected several times and are highly unreliable.
Interestingly you can also change the icon of most device to a large variety of
existing devices so that they would look more realistic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another feature I find pretty cool is the floor plan. You can create plans for
each floor of your house and then create rooms inside and finally attach devices
to each room and place inside the plan. Unfortunately, to draw the plan, you'll
have to use an external tool. I've used floorplanner for this, but you may use
any plan you have as long as you have an image.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is my floor plan with the devices (the scale is terribly off :P) :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Domoticz Floor Plan" class="align-center" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/domoticz_floorplan.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that you can directly see the status of each of your sensors in each room.
Moreover, you can also activate some devices directly from the floor plan as
well :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Normally, my Somfy blinds are supposed to work with the RFLink controller.
I have managed to control my blinds but only when the RFLink was within 50
centimeters of the Blinds, which is clearly not acceptable. I don't know from
where the problem comes. It may come from my Blinds controller inside the wall
or may come from bad antenna of the RFLink or from a bug in RFLink, so from now
I cannot control my blinds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have several D-Link cameras at home. You can also add cameras to Domoticz, but
don't expect a lot of support on this side. It's pretty poor indeed. The only
useful you can do in Domoticz with Cameras is to take a screenshot from them.
You cannot control the Camera or even have a decent video stream and cannot do
motion detection directly. I hope that the Camera support will improve in the
future. One thing that would be good is to add a view of the cameras in the
floor plan, but it is not possible currently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I did is to use Zoneminder to manage the cameras and send alert to Domoticz
when motion is detect with the REST API of Domoticz. Unfortunately that means
two systems to manage the Cameras. Zoneminder is a very good piece of software,
but one of the ugliest I've ever seen (even I can do a better web interface...)
and quite obscure to configure. But the numbers of cameras it can handle and the
capabilities to control the camera is very very powerful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="events-and-actions"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Events and actions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No home automation system would be complete without an events and rules system.
In Domoticz, you have several ways to create rules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first solution is to create group. A group is simply a set of switches that
are all activated together. This is pretty limited, but can be useful. The
second solution is a scene. A scene is activated by a device and can set several
switches to on or off after the activation. The problem with this is that you
have to listen for an action as activation, you cannot use an existing device or
a rule with a value. For me, these two possibilities are way too limited and
I don't really a reason to use them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best solution is to script an handler. For that, there are two ways, either
you define visually your script with blocky, for instance:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Domoticz Blockly Rule" class="align-center" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/domoticz_blockly.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This seemed so cool that I wanted to do all my rules with that. Unfortunately,
it is really limited. The main limitation is that you cannot nest if blocks. In
fact the interface lets you do, but it doesn't work afterwards. The other
limitation is that it has no notion of time. For instance, it's very hard to
create an action if a computer is shutdown for more than 60 seconds. You can do
it, but you end up creating virtual devices which are turned off after some
delay and it gets really complicated really soon...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, I used Lua script directly. These scripts have the information about
the last values of each device and the last updated time as well. It's much
easier with that to create powerful rules especially when you want a notion of
time. There are plenty of examples on the Domoticz forum about very powerful
rules that you can create. Unfortunately, there are some limitations. For
instance, you cannot send several actions to the same device in the same script
Moreover, you also have to decode the values of the sensors yourself. For
instance, for a temperature and humidity sensor, you'll have to parse the values
and extract the one you need by hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far, I haven't created many rules, only four. The first rule is that with the
push of one remote button I can power on my smart socket and turn on one of my
computers in my office. Then, if both the computers on this smart sockets have
been off for more than 60 seconds, the power is shut off on the smart socket.
And I have done almost the same for my media center and TV in my living room.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the future, I'll probably only use the Lua scripting capability. In my
opinion, it's better to have all the scripts in the same language for
maintainability reasons. Once my futures devices arrive, I'll have a few more
rules to code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="conclusion"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To wrap up, I'd say that I'm pretty satisfied with my new home automation system
with Domoticz. It's not a perfect tool, but it has a lot of features and is
working quite well in general. I would recommend you to try it if you want
a good home automation system, fully featured and relatively easy to use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've several more things planned for this system. I plan to test a real motion
sensor rather than rely only on the cameras which are focused on the doors and
windows. I also plan to add an outdoor temperature sensor. And more
interestingly, I'm going to try to integrate smart bulbs from Milight to be able
to control my lights from the system. These are the shot term projects that
I want to do, but I have many more ideas!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm also sure that there are some features from Domoticz that I have overlooked
or not discovered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll probably write more posts on Home Automation on the coming months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more information on Domoticz, you can consult
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://domoticz.com/"&gt;the official Domoticz website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Home Automation</category><category>Personal</category><category>projects</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2017/01/new-home-automation-system-with-domoticz.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 08 Jan 2017 15:08:42 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Asgard: Home Automation project</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2016/08/asgard-home-automation-project.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I have updated my asgard project to make it finally useful for me, so I figured
I'd present the project now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Asgard is my project of home automation based on a Raspberry Pi. I started this
project after Ninja Blocks kickstarter company went down and I was left with
useless sensors. So I figured why not have fun creating my own :P I know there
are some other projects out there that are pretty good, but I wanted to do some
more low level stuff for once, so what the hell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, everything is written in C++, no surprise here. The project is built
upon a server / drivers architecture. The drivers and the server are talking via
network sockets, so they can be on different machines.  The server is displaying
the data it got on a web interface and also provide a way to trigger actions of
drivers either from the web interface or through the integrated rules engine.
The data are stored in a database, accessed with CPPSqlite3 (probably going to
be replaced by sqlcpp11) and the web server is handled with mongoose (with a c++
interface).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I must mention that most of the web part of the project was made by a student of
mine, Stéphane Ly, who work on it as part of his study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a picture of the Raspberry Pi system (not very pretty ;) ):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Asgard automation system hardware" class="align-center" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/asgard_hardware.jpg"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I plan to try to fit at least some of it on a nicer box with nicer cables and
such. Moreover, I also plan to add real antennas to the RF transmitter and
receiver, but I haven't received them so far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="sensors"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Sensors&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;asgard support several sensors:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;DHT11 Temperature/Humdity Sensor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;WT450 Temperature/Humdity Sensor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;RF Button&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;IR Remote&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CPU Temperature Sensor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can see the sensors data displayed on the web interface:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Asgard automation system home page" class="align-center" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/asgard_home.png"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="actions"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Actions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are currently a few actions provided by the drivers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wake-On-Lan a computer by its MAC Address&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ITT-1500 smart plugs ON and OFF&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kodi actions: Pause / Play / Next / Previous on Kodi&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are the rules engine:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Asgard automation system rules page" class="align-center" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/asgard_rules.png"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="my-home-automation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;My home automation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm currently using this system to monitor the temperature in my appartment.
Nothing great so far because I don't have enough sensors yet. And now, I'm also
using a wireless button to turn on my power socket, wait 2 seconds and then
power on my Kodi Home Theater with wake on lan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's nothing fancy so far, but it's already better than what I had with Ninja
Blocks, except for the ugly hardware ;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="future"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Future&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are still tons of work on the project and on integration in my home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I'm really dissatisfied with the WT450 sensor, I've ordered new Oregon sensors to try to do better.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I've ordered a few new sensors: Door intrusion detector and motion detector&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The rules system needs to be improve to support multiple conditions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I plan to add a simple state system to the asgard server&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are a lot of refactorings necessary in the code and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, I don't know when I'll work on this again, my work on this project is
pretty episodic to say the least.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="code"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Code&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The code is, as always, available on Github. There are multiple repositories:
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/search?q=user%3Awichtounet+asgard"&gt;all asgard repositories&lt;/a&gt;.
It's not that much code for now, about 2000 lines of code, but some of it may be
useful. If you plan to use the system, keep in mind that it was never tested out
of my environment and that there is no documentation so far, but don't hesitate
to open Issues on Github if you have questions or post a comment here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>asgard</category><category>Home Automation</category><category>Personal</category><category>projects</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2016/08/asgard-home-automation-project.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 27 Aug 2016 20:28:16 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Upgrade to Nikola 7</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2015/11/upgrade-to-nikola-7.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I've finally taken the time to upgrade the website to Nikola 7 (it is about time, I know...).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The migration worked flawlessly, I simply had to update configuration to migrate deprecated and renamed tags and it worked really well. I also had to add a comma to the COMPILERS list because of the use of Python 3.3 now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you may have seen, I haven't posted in a while. I had quite some work for my thesis as well as for the courses I give at my school and I started playing Path Of Exile with took quite a bit of my free time :) I'll try to give some updates on the project I'm working on to make this blog live again.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Nikola</category><category>Personal</category><category>The site</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2015/11/upgrade-to-nikola-7.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 20 Nov 2015 09:56:32 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Migrated from Wordpress to Nikola</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2014/03/migrated-from-wordpress-to-nikola.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;As you're reading this post, the site has been migrated from WordPress to &lt;a href="http://www.getnikola.com/"&gt;Nikola&lt;/a&gt; and is now hosted on Github. Nikola is a static site generator. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Reasons of the migration&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had several reasons to migrate my website from WordPress to a static site generator: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I was getting tired of WordPress. It not a bad tool, but it is becoming heavier and heavier. I think that one of the biggest problems is that you need tons of plugins to make a fully-functional blog. I had more than 20 plugins. And each time you upgrade WordPress, you run into problems with the addons. In my opinion, while I understand why you need plugins for syntax highlighting for instance, you should not need any plugin for performances or security. Moreover, when you think of it a blog is not dynamic, I write less than a post a week and most bloggers write about once a day, in the computer science's sense, it is not dynamic at all. So why bother with a database ?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I wanted to use my favourite tools for modifying my blog: the shell and vim. I don't think that wysiwyg editors are really adding any value to editing. I am faster writing posts in vim than I'm in a web editor. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I wanted to be able to edit my website offline. With a static generator, as long as you have the files on your computer, you can edit your site and even browse it offline. You can then deploy it on the internet later when you are online. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I wanted to host my blog at Github Pages, for fun! Moreover, I had some uptime issues with my host with quite some downtime in the last months. And it saves me some bucks each year, at least it was not a strong factor. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The quest for a good static blog generator&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has been several months already since I started thinking about migrating my blog. I had quite a hard time to find a suitable blog generator. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I needed something: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Simple&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Completely usable in command line&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;With a WordPress import feature&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fast: I didn't wanted to spend a long time generating the website. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Actively developed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem is that there are tens of static site generator. I considered several of them. The most well known is Jekyll. It really looks fine, but I have to say that I HATE Ruby. I think it is an horrible language with an even more horrible environment. I cannot even have Ruby installed on my computer. So I didn't spend a long time considering Jekyll. I also considered Hyde, which is the evil brother of Jekyll, but I think that it was missing documentation to be completely usable for me. I also though of Pelican, but I was not convinced with it. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't know how, but at first I didn't found about Nikola. It was only after some time that I came across Nikola by pure luck. Once I came accross Nikola, I directly was convinced by it. Nikola is written in Python and has a large set of features but still keeps the whole think very simple. Generation of the website is pretty fast. Even though I don't like Python very much, I'm able to stand its environment and if necessary I can hack around a bit. I also considered Hyde, which is the evil brother of Jekyll, but I think that it was missing documentation to be completely usable for me. I also though of Pelican, but I was not convinced with it. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't know how, but at first I didn't found about Nikola. It was only after some time that I came across Nikola by pure luck. Once I found about Nikola, I directly was convinced by it. Nikola is written in Python and has a large set of features but still keeps the whole think very simple. Generation of the website is pretty fast. Even though I don't like Python very much, I'm able to stand its environment and if necessary I can hack around a bit. So I decided to try the complete migration. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The migration&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once I decided to migrate to Nikola, I directly started by importing my WordPress site into a Git repository. This process is quite simple, you just have to export and XML dump from WordPress and then import it into Nikola with the *import_wordpress" command. This already downloads the necessary images and resources and create posts and pages corresponding to your site. It also generates some redirections from the old URL scheme to the new one. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, there is still some manual work to be done. Here is what I had to do after I imported my WordPress site into Nikola: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As syntax highlighting was done by a plugin, I had to convert it to Markdown myself. This was quite easy, just a matter of &lt;em&gt;sed&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I was not satisfied with the default templates so I enhanced it myself. As I'm a very poor web developer and even poorer web designer, it took me a long time, even if it is a simple one. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I wanted to add some visibility to the comments, so I used Disqus API to create Most Popular and Recent Comments widgets. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I had to create some redirections by myself for the tags and categories. This was again just a matter of simple shell commands. I filled a bug about it so it'll probably be fixed in the near future.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I tried to improve the performances of the generated website, but I'm still gonna work on this later, the calls to Disqus and Google javascripts are the ones that takes the most of the load time. I think that a static site could be even faster. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finally, I really missed the options to have related posts generated for each posts, so I hacked a simple way to include them for each posts. The related posts are generated using a very simple algorithm. I'll soon write a post about how I have done this. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Except from these things, it hasn't been too hard to migrate to Nikola. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until now I'm really satisfied with Nikola and I hope this will motivate me to write more blog posts in the coming months. I hope you'll find the website as enjoyable as before (or even more :) ). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are interested, you can read the &lt;a href="http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2014/03/migrated-from-wordpress-to-nikola.wp"&gt;source of this blog post&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though I tried my best to avoid 404 or problems with the new site, I'm pretty sure there will be some issues in the following weeks. If you happen to found a dead link or some part of the website is not working for you, don't hesitate to comment this post and I'll my best to fix it. If you have suggestions on how to improve the site or have a question about the process of migrating a website from Wordpress to Nikola, I'd be glad to answer you. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Nikola</category><category>Personal</category><category>The site</category><category>WordPress</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2014/03/migrated-from-wordpress-to-nikola.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 23 Mar 2014 21:23:21 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Why and how I completely left Windows for Linux</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2013/07/why-how-left-windows-for-linux.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;For years now, I always kept a dual-boot at home with a Linux system (currently Gentoo) and a Windows system. At work, I only use Gentoo. This week-end, I decided to completely remove it and migrate the applications I used on Windows to my Gentoo system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Why Windows ?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So first things first, why was I keeping the Windows system ? For several reasons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Games :) Unfortunately, most of the games I play are not natively compatible with Linux.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Office. I always liked Microsoft Office. As I hate OpenOffice/LibreOffice, I never wanted to remove it For schools we always had several teachers forcing us to use Microsoft document formats.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Hardware support. I always found that hardware support in Windows was great. Most of the time when you add new peripheral, there is nothing, it just works, which is great.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Applications. I always had some applications that I didn't found good enough Linux equivalents for. For instance, Newsleecher, iTunes or TaggedFrog.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, I work on Linux for years now and I would like to have to work on Windows again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;What Changed ?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This weekend I upgraded my hardware configuration (Motherboard, CPU and RAM). I was afraid that I had to reinstall my Linux configurations (because of Gentoo compiled with march=native), but I never thought that I would have to reinstall Windows. I turned out the contrary: my Gentoo installation worked just fine and my Windows totally crashed (BSOD at each startup). I finally made it through Windows after disabled AHCI mode on my motherboard, but then activation was invalidated (of course...) and online activation was not working. I decided to install the new chipset drivers and launch the Windows update and after that, Windows decided to boot without any USB support (WTF...). After that, I decided that Windows what not so great at all for   hardware support...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another reason I left Windows is Windows 8. I find that Window 7 was really great, but I really don't like Windows 8 and I would never have upgraded my Seven to it. Moreover, I recently bought Microsoft Office 2013 and it turned that I had to create an account at Microsoft to install it... Seriously ??? And moreover, it turned out to be worse thant Office 2010 (which, again, was great).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So all these reasons made me remove Windows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;How to migrate everything to Linux ?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, I had no problem with my data. Most of my data are on a personal NAS and the remaining is on Dropbox, so no problem on this side.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I still had some problems to resolve. First of all, I needed my games to run on Linux. I currently play only Diablo III. As I had received a year free of &lt;a title="Crossover" href="http://www.codeweavers.com/products/"&gt;Crossover&lt;/a&gt;, I decided to give it a try. Crossover is based on Wine and ensures that some software are running correctly under it and provide technical support. After some tuning, Diablo III was running almost flawlessly on my Gentoo machine :) Problem 1 solved. I will totally buy a license of Crossover, once my free year is over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I still add some applications to replace. I use iTunes as my main music player and library manager. Some time ago, I tried a lot of programs like Amarok/Rythmbox/Banshee, but I didn't liked them a lot and they were not running very well on large library of music files. This time, I tried &lt;a title="Clementine" href="http://www.clementine-player.org/"&gt;Clementine&lt;/a&gt;. Even if not very beautiful, it had all the features I needed and worked very well. I decided to stick with it. Another program I like a lot on Windows is TaggedFrog. It is a very simple program allowing to put tags on any file on the system and then search by tag on them. I haven't found a total equivalent. I first tried Tracker that is a Gnome project, but I was not satisfied with the search interface. After that, I tried the very simple &lt;a title="TMSU" href="http://tmsu.org/"&gt;TMSU&lt;/a&gt;. It is a command-line based tagging manager. All the tagging must be done in command line. In my case, it is not a problem, as I don't mind using the command-line and I don't tag files very often. What is very interesting about TMSU is that it can create a virtual file system (based on FUSE). In this file system, you have all your tags  as folder and you can see directly all the files of each tag. Moreover, you can directly make cross search (has tag X and Y and Z) by just going down in the tag folder. It is really great and has everything I needed. Finally, I also needed something to replace Newsleecher. I haven't found something as great (especially no replacement for the Supersearch function), but I installed &lt;a title="Sabnzbd" href="http://sabnzbd.org/"&gt;Sabnzbd&lt;/a&gt; which works really well and is very simple. For now, I just use the web interface and haven't installed any other front-end, but that will perhaps change in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I haven't replaced Office for now on. It occurred to me that since I left school, I haven't used it a lot, so that will probably not be a problem anymore. I will change to write the few letters I have to write on Latex and if I have Office documents, I'll probably read them on Google Drive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if I lost a lot of time with all that, I think it is a great think. It makes one less configuration to maintain and some less costs on the future. Moreover, I will save some time, because I won't have to switch between Linux and Windows for different tasks. And now, I have a second SSD ready for something else, either for RAID 1 to ensure redundancy on Linux or to mount on a server, I'll see later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will probably have some more problems in the future, but I'm convinced that there will be Linux solutions to it :)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Gentoo</category><category>Linux</category><category>Others</category><category>Personal</category><category>Windows</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2013/07/why-how-left-windows-for-linux.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2013 06:24:25 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Back in Berkeley, California</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2012/09/back-in-berkeley-california.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I arrived yesterday to Berkeley, California.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just like I did my Bachelor thesis in Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory (LBNL), I will do my Master Thesis there too. The thesis will last a bit less than a semester.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During my Master Thesis I will try to use profiling samples from the Linux perf tools in GCC or Clang to optimize processor cache usage (avoid cache and page faults).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will try to publish some posts about that during the semester if I have time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Compilers</category><category>gcc</category><category>Others</category><category>Personal</category><category>The site</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2012/09/back-in-berkeley-california.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 13 Sep 2012 08:35:43 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Merry Christmas</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2011/12/merry-christmas.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;A bit late, but better late than never : Merry Christmas to all the readers of this blog :)&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>Others</category><category>Personal</category><category>The site</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2011/12/merry-christmas.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Dec 2011 00:12:57 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>New Wordpress theme for the site</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2011/11/new-theme-site.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;After a long time with the old F2 theme, I decided to choose a more modern design. I chose the WP Plus design which is based on the Google Plus Design. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that this design is more practical and cleaner for the users and more comfortable. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, I also took some time to change some of my addons. I replaced All In One SEO with Wordpress SEO plugin from Joost de Valk. I think that this plugin is better than the first one, but more of that, it also replaced one addon generating the XML sitemap and helped me adding a breadcrumb to the site. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope that these changes will improve the user experience on my website. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you encounter any kind of problems with the new design, don't hesitate to let a comment or to contact me.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Personal</category><category>The site</category><category>Web</category><category>WordPress</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2011/11/new-theme-site.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 18 Nov 2011 00:56:17 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Diploma Thesis : Inlining Assistance for large-scale object-oriented applications</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2011/10/diploma-thesis-inlining-assistance-for-large-scale-object-oriented-applications.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;One month ago, my diploma thesis has been accepted and I got my Bachelor of Science in Computer Science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I made my diploma thesis at Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory, Berkeley, California. I was in the team responsible of the developmenet of the ATLAS Software for the LHC in Cern. The title of my thesis is &lt;strong&gt;Inlining Assistance for large-scale object-oriented applications&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal of this project was to create a C++ analyzer to find the best functions and call sites to inline. The input of the analyzer is a call graph generated by CallGrind of the Valgrind project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The functions and call sites to inline are computed using a heuristic, called the temperature. This heuristic is based on the cost of calling the given function, the frequency of calls and the size of the function. The cost of calling a function is based on the number of parameters, the virtuality of the function and the shared object the function is located in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The analyzer is also able to find clusters of call sites. A cluster is a set of hot call sites related to each other. It can also finds the functions that should be moved from one library to the other or the function that should not be virtual by testing the use of each function in a class hierarchy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To achieve this project, it has been necessary to study in details how a function is called on the Linux platform. The inlining optimization has also been studied to know what were the advantages and the problems of this technique.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To retrieve the information about the sizes and the virtuality of the function, it has been necessary to read the shared libraries and executables files. For that, we used &lt;em&gt;libelf&lt;/em&gt;. The virtuality of a function is calculated by reading each virtual table and searching for the function in the virtual tables content.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The graph manipulation is made by the &lt;em&gt;Boost Graph Library&lt;/em&gt;. As it was an advanced library, it has helped me improving my skills in specific topics like templates, traits or Template Metaprogramming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The analyzer is able to run on the Linux platform on any program that has been compiled using gcc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="more"&gt;&lt;a href="http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2011/10/diploma-thesis-inlining-assistance-for-large-scale-object-oriented-applications.html"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Boost</category><category>C++</category><category>Compilers</category><category>gcc</category><category>Linux</category><category>Optimization</category><category>Performances</category><category>Personal</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2011/10/diploma-thesis-inlining-assistance-for-large-scale-object-oriented-applications.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2011 06:44:17 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>No more ads on the site !</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2011/06/no-more-ads-on-the-site.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hi,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you have perhaps noticed, there is no more Google Adsense on the site. I removed them for several reasons :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;They were not really visually good&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;They slowed down the site by a factor of two&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;That gave a bad image of the site&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;This is not the main goal of the website to make money&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;They didn't made enough money to counter the previous disadvantages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So you will now have a faster and a bit nicer website to look at :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only page that contains ads on the site is the search because of the use of Google Custom Search that includes Google Ads, but this is not my ads. I will perhaps consider to add another search system in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope this will make the site more enjoyable&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;P.S. Is there is still a page with ads that I have forgotten to update, just let a comment with the URL of the page and I will remove the ads&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Google</category><category>Personal</category><category>The site</category><category>Web</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2011/06/no-more-ads-on-the-site.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 28 Jun 2011 06:33:07 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Now writing from Berkeley, California</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2011/05/now-writing-from-berkeley-california.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hi, &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This message has been written from California, where I'm for 3 months. I'm making my bachelor final project in Berkeley Labs. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll certainly give some informations about the project and my researches during the next months. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope that I'll have the time to write more articles this next months as I've made the last months... I had a lot of work at school and no motivation to write.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Others</category><category>Personal</category><category>The site</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2011/05/now-writing-from-berkeley-california.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 28 May 2011 20:38:43 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Save time with the Gmail Priority Inbox</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2010/09/save-time-with-the-gmail-priority-inbox.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Some days ago, Gmail released a new feature, the &lt;strong&gt;Priority Inbox&lt;/strong&gt;. Actually, the feature is not released on all accounts, but if it is released on yours, you can see a message "Try Gmail Priority Inbox", in top right high corner, just after your user name.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you activated this new inbox, you will see two inbox, the new Priority Inbox on top and the old Inbox. The Inbox has not changed, but now you can use the Priority Inbox. In this view, you will see your messages sorted in two categories, the first one contains the important unread messages and the second one contains all the other messages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you found an error, namely a non-important message tagged as important or the contrary, you have two new buttons :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://baptiste-wicht.com/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/Gmail-Buttons.png"&gt;&lt;img class="size-full wp-image-1018" title="GMail Priority Buttons" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/Gmail-Buttons.png" alt="GMail Priority Buttons" width="77" height="32"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With these buttons, you can move a message from the priority messages to the others and vice versa. When you do that, the algorithm between the sorting will save your action and try to improve the efficiency of the Priority Inbox to not make the same error again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this time, I'm completely happy with this new feature, I've had only one message marked as important that was not, but it's all. I think it's a great tool that Google has offerred to us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want more informations, let's watch this video from Google :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width="640" height="385"&gt;&lt;param name="movie" value="http://www.youtube.com/v/5nt3gE9dGHQ?fs=1&amp;amp;amp"&gt;&lt;param name="allowFullScreen" value="true"&gt;&lt;param name="allowscriptaccess" value="always"&gt;&lt;embed src="http://www.youtube.com/v/5nt3gE9dGHQ?fs=1&amp;amp;amp" type="application/x-shockwave-flash" allowscriptaccess="always" allowfullscreen="true" width="640" height="385"&gt;&lt;/embed&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Google</category><category>Personal</category><category>Web</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2010/09/save-time-with-the-gmail-priority-inbox.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 04 Sep 2010 03:44:27 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Holidays</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2010/08/holidays.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Monday, I will go on holidays for one week. I'll not have internet except on my smartphone, so I'll not post on this blog during one week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will just approve comments and perhaps answer to comments if this is necessary, but this is all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, to next week.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Others</category><category>Personal</category><category>The site</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2010/08/holidays.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 15 Aug 2010 10:37:52 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Wordpress 3.0 installed !</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2010/06/wordpress-3-0-installed.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Wordpress 3.0 (Thelounious) has been released this week. I just updated the blog with the new version. I had no problem during the upgrade process, all automatically. Good job !&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This major release of Wordpress solve more tan 1200 bug, add several performance improvements and add several new features :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Merge of Wordpress MU : You can now add several different blogs on the same installation of Wordpress&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;New default Theme : Twenty Ten&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Bulk updates for the plugins. You can updates all your plugins and themes at once.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt; More possibilities for the themes : custom background, headers, shortlinks, ...&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Custom post types&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Lighter interface&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want more information, this video can help you :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;embed src="http://v.wordpress.com/wp-content/plugins/video/flvplayer.swf?ver=1.21" type="application/x-shockwave-flash" width="640" height="360" wmode="transparent" seamlesstabbing="true" allowfullscreen="true" allowscriptaccess="always" overstretch="true" flashvars="guid=BQtfIEY1&amp;amp;width=640&amp;amp;height=360&amp;amp;locksize=no&amp;amp;dynamicseek=false&amp;amp;qc_publisherId=p-18-mFEk4J448M" title='Introducing WordPress 3.0 "Thelonious"'&gt;&lt;/embed&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Personal</category><category>The site</category><category>Web</category><category>WordPress</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2010/06/wordpress-3-0-installed.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 19 Jun 2010 07:07:59 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>I just passed the SCJP exam !</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2010/04/passed-scjp-exam.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I'm happy to say that I passed the Sun Certified Java Programmer for Java SE 6.0 this morning :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I passed the exam with 93%. I'm really happy of my score. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To prepare this exam, I read the &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/SCJP-Certified-Programmer-Java-310-065/dp/0071591060/ref=sr_1_2?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;s=books&amp;amp;qid=1270728614&amp;amp;sr=1-2"&gt;SCJP Sun Certified Programmer for Java 6 Exam 310-065&lt;/a&gt; and exercise the chapters for which I wasn't good enough. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So i started my exam this morning at 8.30 (Switzerland time) and after 2 hours of work, I was happy to see my score and to rest my poor brain. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So now i'm waiting of the certificate sended by post.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Java</category><category>Personal</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2010/04/passed-scjp-exam.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 08 Apr 2010 06:14:03 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Welcome to my new website !</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2010/03/welcome-to-my-new-website.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Welcome to my new english website :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've moved all my english stuff from Developpez.com to make here a completely english website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope you'll find here some interesting stuff. I will publish articles and posts about Java, Spring, Swing, OSGi, Hardware and Web and perhaps others technologies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don't hesitate to say me what you think about this website.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Others</category><category>Personal</category><category>The site</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2010/03/welcome-to-my-new-website.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 17 Mar 2010 03:21:29 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>