<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>Blog blog("Baptiste Wicht"); (Posts about Prolog)</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/</link><description></description><atom:link rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" href="http://baptiste-wicht.com/categories/prolog.xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 04 Jun 2017 20:17:48 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Solve Einstein’s Riddle using Prolog</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2010/09/solve-einsteins-riddle-using-prolog.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;This week, we started learning Prolog at school. So to exercise, I choose the Einstein's Riddle. Einstein wrote this riddle in the 19th century. He stated that only 2% of the population can solve it by mind. Personnally, I'm not of this two %, I needed paper and pens to solve it. But this is not the them of the post, so let's use Prolog to solve it. I will present my solution, there is certainly other solutions, and certainly better, but it makes only some days that I started learning this language and this new kind of developing, logical programming. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the riddle as stated by Einstein :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;In a street there are five houses, painted five different colours.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;In each house lives a person of different nationality&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;These five homeowners each drink a different kind of beverage, smoke different brand of cigar and keep a different pet.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question is : Who owns the fish ?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And there are 15 hints :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The Brit lives in a red house.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The Swede keeps dogs as pets.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The Dane drinks tea.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The Green house is next to, and on the left of the White house.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The owner of the Green house drinks coffee.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The person who smokes Pall Mall rears birds.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The owner of the Yellow house smokes Dunhill.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The man living in the centre house drinks milk.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The Norwegian lives in the first house.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The man who smokes Blends lives next to the one who keeps cats.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The man who keeps horses lives next to the man who smokes Dunhill.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The man who smokes Blue Master drinks beer.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The German smokes Prince.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The Norwegian lives next to the blue house.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The man who smokes Blends has a neighbour who drinks water.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let's start with the code !&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="more"&gt;&lt;a href="http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2010/09/solve-einsteins-riddle-using-prolog.html"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Others</category><category>Prolog</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2010/09/solve-einsteins-riddle-using-prolog.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 22 Sep 2010 05:01:30 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>