<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Blog blog("Baptiste Wicht"); (Posts about Releases)</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/</link><description></description><atom:link type="application/rss+xml" rel="self" href="http://baptiste-wicht.com/categories/releases.xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 14 Sep 2017 19:12:48 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>budgetwarrior 0.4.2 - Budget summary and improved fortune reports</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2017/09/budgetwarrior-042-budget-summary-improved-fortune-reports.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Almost three years ago, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2014/09/budgetwarrior-041-expense-templates-and-year-projection.html"&gt;I published the version 0.4.1 of budgetwarrior&lt;/a&gt;. Since then, I've been using this tool almost every day to manage my personal budget. This is the only tool I use to keep track of my expenses and earnings and it makes a great tool for me. I recently felt that it was missing a few features and added them and polished a few things as well and release a new version with all the new stuff. This new version is probably nothing fancy, but a nice upgrade of the tool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don't pay too much attention to the values in the images since I've randomized
all the data for the purpose of this post (new feature, by the way :P).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="new-summary-view"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;New summary view&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've added a new report with &lt;code&gt;budget summary&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="/images/budgetwarrior_042_summary.png" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/budgetwarrior_042_summary.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This view gives concise information about the current state of your accounts. It
also gives information about your yearly and monthly objectives. Finally, it
also gives information about the last two fortune values that you've set.
I think this make a great kind of dashboard to view most of the information. If
your terminal is large enough, the three parts will be shown side by side.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="improved-fortune-report"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Improved fortune report&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've made a few improvements to the &lt;code&gt;budget fortune&lt;/code&gt; view:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="/images/budgetwarrior_042_fortune.png" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/budgetwarrior_042_fortune.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It now display the time between the different fortune values and it compute the
average savings (or avg losses) per day in each interval and in average from the
beginning of the first value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="various-changes"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Various changes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The balance does not propagate over the years anymore. This should mainly change
the behaviour of &lt;code&gt;budget overview&lt;/code&gt;. I don't think it was very
smart to propagate it all the time. The balance now starts at zero for each
year. If you want the old system, you can use the multi_year_balance=true option
in the .budgetrc configuration file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The recurring expenses do not use an internal configuration value. This does not
change anything for the behaviour, but means that if you sync between different
machines, it will avoid a lot of possible conflicts :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fixed a few bugs with inconsistency between the different views and reports.
Another bug that was fixed is that &lt;code&gt;budget report&lt;/code&gt; was not always displaying the
first month of the year correctly, this is now fixed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The graphs display in &lt;code&gt;budget report&lt;/code&gt; are now automatically adapted to width of
your terminal. Finally, the &lt;code&gt;budget overview&lt;/code&gt; command also displays more
information about the comparison with the previous month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="installation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Installation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are on Gentoo, you can install it using layman:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
layman -a wichtounet
emerge -a budgetwarrior
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are on Arch Linux, you can use this &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/StreakyCobra/aur-budgetwarrior"&gt;AUR repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For other systems, you'll have to install from sources:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
git clone --recursive git://github.com/wichtounet/budgetwarrior.git
cd budgetwarrior
make
sudo make install
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="conclusion"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A brief tutorial is available on Github: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/wichtounet/budgetwarrior/wiki/Start-tutorial"&gt;Starting guide&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are interested by the sources, you can download them on Github:
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/wichtounet/budgetwarrior"&gt;budgetwarrior&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have any suggestion for a new feature or an improvement to the tool or
you found a bug, please post an issue on Github, I'd be glad to help you. You
can post a comment directly on this post :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have any other comment, don't hesitate to contact me, either by letting a
comment on this post or by email.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope that this application can be useful to some of you command-line adepts :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>budgetwarrior</category><category>C++</category><category>Gentoo</category><category>Linux</category><category>Releases</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2017/09/budgetwarrior-042-budget-summary-improved-fortune-reports.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 14 Sep 2017 18:42:39 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Aggregator Plugin : Display global metrics in Sonarqube</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2015/11/aggregator-plugin-display-global-metrics-in-sonarqube.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Recently, I wanted to know how many lines of code I had on my Sonar server with all my C++ projects. Sonarsource proposes a commercial plugins (Views) that allows to do that (and much more...), but I didn't wanted to pay thousands of dollars simply to get a total of my lines of code, therefore I wrote a very  simple Sonar plugin to compute some global metrics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This plugin is very simple, it only provides a global widgets that aggregates some stats over all your projects. For instance, here is the results on my Sonar server:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="/images/aggregator_widget.png" class="align-center" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/aggregator_widget.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The plugin is freely available on Github: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/wichtounet/aggregator-plugin"&gt;https://github.com/wichtounet/aggregator-plugin&lt;/a&gt; . However, it has only be tested on my Sonar server (4.5.2) and it is my first Sonar plugin, so it may not work everywhere. If you experience issues, don't hesitate to open an issue on Github or to propose a Pull Request.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can install the plugin by putting the .jar file (from the Github Releases page) into your sonar/extensions/plugins directory and restart Sonar. You should then have access to a new global widget that you can add to a dashboard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope this plugin helps some of you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>projects</category><category>Releases</category><category>Sonar</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2015/11/aggregator-plugin-display-global-metrics-in-sonarqube.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 20 Nov 2015 10:37:55 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>budgetwarrior 0.4.1 - Expense templates and year projection</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2014/09/budgetwarrior-041-expense-templates-and-year-projection.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I've been able to finish the version 0.4.1 of budgetwarrior before I though :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="expense-templates"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Expense templates&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The "most useful" new feature of this release is the ability to create template
for expenses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For that, you can give an extra parameter to budget expense add:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
budget expense add template name
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will works exactly the same as creating a new expense expect that it will
be saved as a template. Then, the next time you do:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
budget expense add template name
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A new expense will be created with the date of the day and with the name and
amount saved into the template. You can create as many templates as you want as
long as they have different names. You can see all the templates you have by
using 'budget expense template'. A template can be deleted the exact same as an
expense with 'budget expense delete id'.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think this is very useful for expense that are made several times a month, for
instance a coffee at your workplace. The price should not change a lot and it is
faster to just use the template name rather than entering all the information
again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="year-prediction"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Year prediction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can now see what would be next year if you changed a bit your expenses. For
instance, how much would you still have at the end of the year if you increased
your house expenses by 20% and reduced your insurances by 5% ?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 'budget predict' can be used for that purpose. You can enter a multiplier
for each account in your budget and a new year will be "predicted" based on
the expenses of the current year multiplied by the specified multiplier:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="/images/budget_041_prediction.png" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/budget_041_prediction.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that this feature can be very useful if you want to estimate how your
budget will be for moving to a more expensive house or another insurance for
instance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="various-changes"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Various changes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two accounts can be merged together with the 'budget account migrate' command.
This command will move all expenses from an account to another and adapt the
amount of the target account. The source account will be deleted. This supports
migrated accounts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 'budget wish list' command will now display the mean accuracy of your
predictions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You don't need Boost anymore for this project. The only remaining dependency is
libuuid. I will perhaps remove it in the next version since the UUID are not
used in the application for now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The command 'budget gc' will clean the IDs of all your data in order to fill the
holes and make all the IDs contiguous. It is mostly a feature for order-freaks
like me who do not like to have holes in a sequence of identifiers ;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was a bug in the monthly report causing the scale to be displayed
completely moved, it is now fixed:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/wichtounet/budgetwarrior/develop/screenshots/budget_report.png" src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/wichtounet/budgetwarrior/develop/screenshots/budget_report.png"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="installation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Installation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are on Gentoo, you can install it using layman:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
layman -a wichtounet
emerge -a budgetwarrior
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are on Arch Linux, you can use this &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/StreakyCobra/aur"&gt;AUR repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For other systems, you'll have to install from sources:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
git clone git://github.com/wichtounet/budgetwarrior.git
cd budgetwarrior
make
sudo make install
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="conclusion"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are interested by the sources, you can download them on Github:
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/wichtounet/budgetwarrior"&gt;budgetwarrior&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have a suggestion for a new features or you found a bug, please post an
issue on Github, I'd be glad to help you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have any comment, don't hesitate to contact me, either by letting a
comment on this post or by email.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>budgetwarrior</category><category>C++</category><category>Gentoo</category><category>Linux</category><category>Releases</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2014/09/budgetwarrior-041-expense-templates-and-year-projection.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 21 Sep 2014 18:53:53 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>pm 0.1.1 - A simple workspace manager for Git projects</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2014/07/pm-011-a-simple-workspace-manager-for-git-projects.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the last month, I've developped a very simple tool in Python: &lt;em&gt;pm&lt;/em&gt;. This tool
allows to check the status of all the Git repositories inside a repository. I've
just released the first version of this tool: pm-0.1.1&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those who are following this blog will perhaps wonder why Python and not C++ :)
The reason is quite simple, I wanted to improve my skills in Python. And what is
better than to develop a project from scratch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="features"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Features&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main feature of this application is to show the status of every projects in
a directory. The status of your projects can be queried by using &lt;code&gt;pm
status&lt;/code&gt;. On my computer this gives something like that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="/images/pm_status.png" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/pm_status.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The state of each branch of each project is shown. There different possible
status (they are cumulative):
* Behind remote: Commits are available on the remote repository
* Ahead of remote: Some local commits are no pushed
* Diverged: Behind and Ahead
* Uncomitted changes: Some changes are not committed
* Clean: Indicates that everything is committed, pushed and pull.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By default, the directory is ~/dev/ but you can change it by passing the
repository to the command, if you pass a relative directory, it will be relative
to home. For instance, here is the status of my doc repositories:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="/images/pm_status_2.png" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/pm_status_2.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another feature that can be useful is that it is able to check the status of
submodules with the -s option:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="/images/pm_status_sm.png" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/pm_status_sm.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can see it supports recursive submodules. For each submodule it will
indicate if there are new commits available or not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;pm is not only able to show status of the projects, it can also fetch the status
of branches from remote by using &lt;code&gt;pm fetch&lt;/code&gt;. All the remote branches are
fetched from remote. It can also automatically update the projects that are
behind remote (equivalent of git pull) with &lt;code&gt;pm update&lt;/code&gt;. Only projects
that can be fast-forwarded are updated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="installation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Installation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to &lt;em&gt;pip&lt;/em&gt;, installation of pm is quite simple:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
pip install pm
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don't want to use pip, you can install it by hand:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
wget https://github.com/wichtounet/pm/archive/0.1.1.tar.gz
tar xf 0.1.1.tar.gz
cd 0.1.1
python setup.py install
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those interested, source code is available &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/wichtounet/pm"&gt;on Github&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have any suggestion for the tool or on the source code, post a comment to
this post ;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Git</category><category>Linux</category><category>Python</category><category>Releases</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2014/07/pm-011-a-simple-workspace-manager-for-git-projects.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 20 Jul 2014 18:52:18 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>budgetwarrior 0.4 - Enhanced wish list and aggregate</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2014/07/budgetwarrior-04-enhanced-wish-list-and-aggregate.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I've just released a new version of my command-line budget manager:
budgetwarrior 0.4.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="enhanced-aggregate-overview"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Enhanced aggregate overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aggregate overviews have been greatly improved. First, there is now a
&lt;em&gt;budget overview month&lt;/em&gt; command that groups all expenses of amonth together.
Here is a possible output:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="/images/budget_04_aggregate_month.png" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/budget_04_aggregate_month.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also possible to use &lt;em&gt;--full&lt;/em&gt; option to also aggregate together the different
accounts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="/images/budget_04_aggregate_month_full.png" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/budget_04_aggregate_month_full.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another new option is &lt;em&gt;--no-group&lt;/em&gt; that disables the grouping by categories:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="/images/budget_04_aggregate_month_full_ng.png" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/budget_04_aggregate_month_full_ng.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, the separator of categories can now be configured with &lt;em&gt;--separator=&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All these options can also be set in the configuration with these options:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;aggregate_full : If set to true, does the same as the --full option.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;aggregate_no_group : If set to true, does the same as the --no-group option.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;aggregate_separator : Sets the separator for grouping.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="enhanced-wish-list"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Enhanced wish list&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The wishes management has also been improved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, each wish can now be set an Urgency and Importance level. This is now
shown in wish status as simple indicators:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="/images/budget_04_wish_status.png" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/budget_04_wish_status.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, the accuracy of the estimation compared to the paid amount is shown in
&lt;em&gt;wish list&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="/images/budget_04_wish_list.png" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/budget_04_wish_list.png"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="various-changes"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Various changes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Objective status now shows more information about the status of the objectives:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="/images/budget_04_objective_status.png" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/budget_04_objective_status.png"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The versioning module has been improved. The &lt;em&gt;versioning sync&lt;/em&gt; does now perform
a commmit as well as pull/push. &lt;em&gt;versioning push&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;versioning pull&lt;/em&gt; and
&lt;em&gt;versioning status&lt;/em&gt; commands have been added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;budget version&lt;/em&gt; command shows the version of budgetwarrior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aliases a now available to make shorted commands:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;budget sync -&amp;gt; budget versioning sync&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;budget aggregate -&amp;gt; budget overview aggregate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="installation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Installation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are on Gentoo, you can install it using layman:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
layman -a wichtounet
emerge -a budgetwarrior
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are on Arch Linux, you can use this &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/StreakyCobra/aur"&gt;AUR repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For other systems, you'll have to install from sources:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
git clone git://github.com/wichtounet/budgetwarrior.git
cd budgetwarrior
make
sudo make install
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="conclusion"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are interested by the sources, you can download them on Github:
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/wichtounet/budgetwarrior"&gt;budgetwarrior&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have a suggestion or you found a bug, please post an issue on Github.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have any comment, don't hesitate to contact me, either by letting a
comment on this post or by email.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>budgetwarrior</category><category>C++</category><category>Gentoo</category><category>Git</category><category>Linux</category><category>Releases</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2014/07/budgetwarrior-04-enhanced-wish-list-and-aggregate.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 06 Jul 2014 08:59:55 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>All Packt Publishing ebooks at $10 for 10 years anniversary</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2014/07/all-packt-publishing-ebooks-at-10-for-10-years-anniversary.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;img alt="/images/packt-10years.jpg" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/images/packt-10years.jpg"&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;To celebrate the 10 years anniversay of Packt Publishing, all of the available
ebooks on &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://bit.ly/1mE9FUz"&gt;Packt Publishing&lt;/a&gt; are available at $10 with
no limit per client.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 10 years, Packt Publishing has published more than 200 titles. Throught its
Open Source Project Royalty Scheme, Packt Publishing supports Open Source
project and already has awarded more than $400'000.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you need something to read or just want to use this occasion to pile some
ebooks, don't hesitate to profit from this superb offer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More information on the official site: &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://bit.ly/1mE9FUz"&gt;http://bit.ly/1mE9FUz&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Books</category><category>Promotion</category><category>Releases</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2014/07/all-packt-publishing-ebooks-at-10-for-10-years-anniversary.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2014 20:56:04 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>eddic 1.2.3 - Better data-flow analysis</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2013/03/eddic-1-2-3-better-data-flow-analysis.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I finally finished the version 1.2.3 of eddic. I have been quite busy finishing my master thesis in february and then taking some vacations in United States, so this version came later than I wanted. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main change is about the speed of the data-flow optimizations. I refactored a lot the data-flow to make it much faster. Some test cases are up to 10 times faster :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are still some work to do for speed of optimizations, but it is much better now. Dead Code Elimination and Constant Propagation still have to be made faster, but now the main bottleneck. In the next version of eddic, the parsing performance will be improved. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inlining performance has also been greatly improved. The functions are considered in topological order of the call graph. This makes it much faster and moreover the resulting code is more efficient too. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are also some improvements of the language. char and bool types now takes only one byte each. Copy constructors for structures containing field of structure type are now automatically generated. The grammar has been enhanced to support postfix operations in for loops. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other improvements have been made to the optimization engine. A new optimization has been implemented: Loop Unswitching. This optimization transforms a code like that: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;lt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;X&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;++&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;){&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;){&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="c1"&gt;//Something&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;else&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="c1"&gt;//Something else&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In some code like that: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;){&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;lt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;X&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;++&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;){&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="c1"&gt;//Something&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;else&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;lt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;X&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;++&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;){&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="c1"&gt;//Something else&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;when a doesn't depend on the loop body. The body of the loops is much faster in the second version. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The induction variable analysis is now able to handle loops with induction variable divided in each iteration. With that new feature, the call: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;123&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;is reduced to&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="sc"&gt;'1'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="sc"&gt;'2'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="sc"&gt;'3'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another small optimization is that variables contributing only to themselves are now correctly identified as dead. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the compiler side, the timing system has been greatly improved to contains almost all part of the compilation process. The timings for the complete compilation is available &lt;a href="https://github.com/wichtounet/eddic/wiki/Performance" title="Performance"&gt;on the wiki&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Future Work&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next version of the EDDI compiler (eddic) will be the version 1.2.4. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Performances will stil be focused for this version. The first change will be to improve the performances of the parsing. Then, I'm gonna try to improve register allocation performances by improving handling of bound registers which I believe is a bottleneck. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are also several refactorings that I think of doing to the code. I will probably also implement new minor language features, but I still don't know what. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, I have to serve in the army the next three weeks, so there won't be any progress these weeks. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Download&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can find the EDDI Compiler sources on the Github repository: &lt;a title="Github repository of eddic" href="https://github.com/wichtounet/eddic"&gt;https://github.com/wichtounet/eddic&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The version is available in the &lt;em&gt;v1.2.3&lt;/em&gt; tag available in the GitHub or directly in the &lt;em&gt;master&lt;/em&gt; branch.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Compilers</category><category>EDDI</category><category>Optimization</category><category>projects</category><category>Releases</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2013/03/eddic-1-2-3-better-data-flow-analysis.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 09 Mar 2013 10:50:27 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>eddic 1.2.2 - Performances, improved optimizations and additions to standard library</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2013/01/eddic-1-2-2-performances-optimization-library.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;These last weeks, I had more work than expected with my Master thesis so it took me longer to finish this new version of eddic. Moreover, I included more stuff than I though in this version. Anyway, I'm happy to announce the version 1.2.2 of eddic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is a minor version regarding the language itself. On the other, there are a lot of changes in the compiler itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the language:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Structures are now correclty copy constructed when passed by value&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;When the same header is included several times accross the program, it is not parsed again&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The vector structure has now functions to insert and remove elements in arbitrary positions&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The functions to print bools, floats and integers are now written in EDDI directly. Only the functions to print chars and raw string are now written in assembly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I worked on improving the performances by improving the constant propagation pass that runs less times now and by tuning a bit the data-flow framework, avoiding virtual calls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another improvement is that all the mtac::Statement types have been merged in mtac::Quadruple, this removes one level of indirection and simplifies several passes. Moreover, there are now directly stored inside a vector and not allocated via shared_ptr. This removes another level of indirection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Put together, these two optimizations improved the performances of the compiler by about 15%. On the other hand, now that printF and printI are written in EDDI, it takes much longer to compile. I will work on that for the next version too. One way to improve the performances will be to tune the ordering of passes and also to tune the passes themselves so that they do more work at once. I will also try to merge constant propagation and offset constant propagation together. They perform very similar work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are also several improvements in the optimization engine:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The loop analysis has been fixed to handle loops bigger than one basic block. There was a problem in my implement of &lt;strong&gt;Lengauer and Tarjan&lt;/strong&gt; making that dominators were not computed.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The optimization engine now create a call graph of the program. This call graph is used to remove unused functions that are called but not reachable from the main function.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;A new analysis pass has been added: pure_analysis. This pass test if a function is pure (no write to pointers or global variables) and thus avoid creating a basic block for it&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The L&lt;strong&gt;oop Invariant Code Motion algorithm&lt;/strong&gt; has been improved to handle more invariants&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Common Subexpression Elimination&lt;/strong&gt; algorithm has been improved to handle more expression&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Induction Variables analysis&lt;/strong&gt; has been reviewed and several bugs have been corrected. It is now a bit complicated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A big bug has been fixed in the handling of the MEMSET LTAC instruction. This will be completely reviewed in the next version (See Future Work).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some analysis starts to become quite complicated. I'm thinking of using SSA in MTAC in order to simplify some of the passes and to easily compute ud-chains. Another thing that I'm thinking is to add a powerful and complete alias analysis that would really improve the efficiency of some passes (offset constant propagation for instance) by making them less conservative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also have removed some memory leaks (will try to remove all of them in the next version). I added a new optimization level: O3. This level enables loop unrolling and complete loop peeling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Future Work&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next version of the EDDI compiler (eddic) will be the version 1.2.3. The inliner will be improved to work directly in the call graph in postorder. That should produce better code. I will also try to improve the inlining heuristics. A first basic version of loop unswitching will be added as well. I will add a small local constant propagation pass for globals. I will also continue to work on the performances of the passes to avoid repeating them too much. MEMSET will be completely reviewed. That should produce smaller and faster code. Until now, the sizes of the types bool and chars were the same as int. They will be optimized to take only 1 byte.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will also continue the improvements of the data structures by merging all ltac::Statement into ltac::Instruction and storing them directly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And there will probably be some bug fixing as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Download&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can find the EDDI Compiler sources on the Github repository: &lt;a title="Github repository of eddic" href="https://github.com/wichtounet/eddic"&gt;https://github.com/wichtounet/eddic&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The version is available in the &lt;em&gt;v1.2.2&lt;/em&gt; tag available in the GitHub or directly in the &lt;em&gt;master&lt;/em&gt; branch.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>C++11</category><category>EDDI</category><category>Releases</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2013/01/eddic-1-2-2-performances-optimization-library.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 26 Jan 2013 15:35:42 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>eddic 1.2.1 - string, concatenation and vector</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2012/12/eddic-1-2-1-string-concatenation-and-vector.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Before preparing myself for New Year's Eve, I decided to finish eddic 1.2.1, and it's done !&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This version is a small one, but add several improvements to the language and to the standard library. Many bugs have been fixed especially in the support of dynamic arrays and structures. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first important change is that string has been renamed to str and that a new struct is available: string. Indeed, str is now a simple raw string where string has more capabilities like concatenation. This new version also supports concatenation of string and int, which was not possible before. In the future, I'll try to add more features to the string class. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another improvement of the standard library is the inclusion of a vector structure. The vector is a dynamic arrays, which means that it can be automatically resized when necessary. For now, the operations available on vector are very few, but more will be added later. Especially, it is not possible now to add elements in the middle of the array, but it will be done, perhaps in the next eddic version or the next after this one. Adding the vector has also meant to add new features to the language. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dynamic arrays of structures is now supported. And, the delete operator can be applied on any left value now, not only variables. It means that "delete a[9];" is now a valid code. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, in the side of the language, printB has been rewritten in EDDI instead of raw assembly. In the next versions, I will continue to rewrite as much as possible of the assembly stuff into EDDI. There are several advantages. The first one is that I don't have to maintain two versions (one for 32 bits and one for 64 bits). Another advantage is that it can profit from the eddic optimizations. And it is more readable and maintainable in EDDI. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A new optimization is now available. If a function is always called with the same value for one of its parameters, the value is propagated inside the function. In the future, it will be improved to suppport propagation for instance in more than X% of the case, creating several versions of the function. The optimizations have also been a bit improved in terms of performance, making some samples much faster to compile than before. Essentially, the removal of dead basic blocks is now made in a way that it doesn't need to be run several times to remove all the dead basic blocks. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The warnings have been improved. Now, no warnings are emitted if some parts of a include are not used. And, if no elements of an included header is used, it will be warned that the include is not necessary. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The error reporting has also been improved a bit. It can now display several errors. For now, it is limited to one error by function. Doing better error reporting, would mean lots of changes in the AST passes which I don't want to do right now. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The hangman application has been fixed. It was a bug in the inliner that was causing this problem. There are now new test cases that verify that the optimizations are done. For instance, there is a test case verifying that the correct loops are removed when necessary. This is done by keeping tracks of counters like removed functions during the optimization. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The source code has also been improved. I now use less shared_ptr and rather rely in storing the elements in standard container and using references directly. It result in much better code. This also improves a bit the performances by having a better data locality. For now, I have handled the given classes: eddic::Function, mtac::Function and mtac::Program, but the next version will handle more critical structures like the basic blocks and the MTAC statements which could improve the performances of the optimization by making iteration faster. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don't hesitate to comment or to contact me if you have any suggestion (or other) about this release or for the future versions of eddic. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;And happy new year !&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Future Work&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next version of the EDDI compiler (eddic) will be the version 1.2.2. In this version, I willl continue the work that I've done by using less shared_ptr and relying on references. I will also continue to improve the interfaces of the different class used. This version will also fix the memory leaks that I spotted in the application. There will also be new improvements on the language side, but minor one and I don't know now which ones I will pick. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Download&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can find the EDDI Compiler sources on the Github repository: &lt;a title="Github repository of eddic" href="https://github.com/wichtounet/eddic"&gt;https://github.com/wichtounet/eddic&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The version is available in the &lt;em&gt;v1.2.1&lt;/em&gt; tag available in the GitHub or directly in the &lt;em&gt;master&lt;/em&gt; branch.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>EDDI</category><category>Releases</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2012/12/eddic-1-2-1-string-concatenation-and-vector.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 31 Dec 2012 18:46:56 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>eddic 1.2.0 - Single inheritance, copy construction</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2012/12/eddic-1-2-0-single-inheritance-copy-constructor.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I'm happy to release the &lt;strong&gt;version 1.2.0 of the EDDI Compiler (eddic)&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This new version introduces several major changes to the language. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, structures can now inherits from another structure. When it is done, the structure can use the members of the parent class. Below is an example of single inheritance in EDDI: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;struct&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;A&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="kt"&gt;float&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="kt"&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;init_a&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(){&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="n"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mf"&gt;55.2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="kt"&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;test_a&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(){&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="n"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mf"&gt;1.1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="k"&gt;struct&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;B&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;extends&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;A&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="kt"&gt;char&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="kt"&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;init_b&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(){&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="n"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="sc"&gt;'B'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="n"&gt;init_a&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="kt"&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;test_b&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(){&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="n"&gt;test_a&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For now, the support remains basic, but it will be improved over time. I will probably add support for virtual functions in the future. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another major improvement to the language is that variable of a custom type can now be assignment, resulting in a call to the copy constructor. If no copy constructor is defined in a structure, it is automatically generated by the compiler. Another improvement to structures is that structures can now contains arrays. Moreover, the members of a structure (fields, constructors, functions, ...) can now be present in any order. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A major change has been made to pointers. The conversions from variables to pointers is no more implicit, it is necessary to use the new &amp;amp; operator to take the address of a variable. I found that this implicit conversions was not really making any sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A function can now return a structure by value. And, member functions can be called from any valid left value. For instance: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;array&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;].&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;function&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;function&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;9&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;is now valid code.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, the switch construct can be used with strings too. This uses the str_equals functions to test which case is valid. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are no big changes in the optimization engine. A new optimization pass has been added performing loop unrolling for loop with known iteration count. The pointer propagation has been fixed to handle pointers on structures resulting in much better code for several samples. The last improvement here is that conditions can be propagated into branches when necessary. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The loop analysis has been improved to directly calculate the number of iterations of each loop and store this result. The list of induction variables is only calculated once now. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The code generation has been slightly improved by saving fewer registers when calling another function. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, there are also some internal changes. The template instantiation depth limit can now configured. Before, infinite template recursion would just fail. The time spent in each optimization can now be computed with the new --timing option. There have been great improvements on the side of the Abstract Syntax Tree. A good part of the expression grammar has been rewritten. With these changes, the grammar is much more powerful than before. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don't hesitate to comment or to contact me if you have any suggestion (or other) about this release or for the future versions of eddic. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'd also like to thank &lt;a href="https://github.com/TyRoXx" title="TyRoXx"&gt;TyRoXx&lt;/a&gt; who has made some improvements in the assembly generation module. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Future Work&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next version of the EDDI compiler (eddic) will be the version 1.2.1. This version will specifically focus on two points. First the usage of strings will be improved with a string class adding features to literal string. The second point will be the performances of the compiler. At this point, the optimization engine is clearly too slow. I will try to make it faster. The list of issues is available &lt;a href="https://github.com/wichtounet/eddic/issues?milestone=2&amp;amp;state=open" title="eddic version 1.2.1"&gt;on Github&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Download&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can find the EDDI Compiler sources on the Github repository: &lt;a title="Github repository of eddic" href="https://github.com/wichtounet/eddic"&gt;https://github.com/wichtounet/eddic&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The version is available in the &lt;em&gt;v1.2.0&lt;/em&gt; tag available in the GitHub or directly in the &lt;em&gt;master&lt;/em&gt; branch.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>C++</category><category>Compilers</category><category>EDDI</category><category>Releases</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2012/12/eddic-1-2-0-single-inheritance-copy-constructor.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 17 Dec 2012 08:20:10 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Packt Publishing celebrates its 1000th IT Book !</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2012/09/packt-publishing-thousandth-book-celebration.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Packt Publishing is about to publish its 1000th title, on the 30th of September, 2012.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Packt published their first book in April 2004. They now have a lot of books on about every subject from web development to IT architecture, games to e-commerce. Their books are known for their high quality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this occasion, they are offering a surprise gift to all their members. If you want to be part of it, you just have to sign up for a free Packt Publishing account. If you're already registered, you don't have anything to do! You need to be registered before the 30th of September in order to get involved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Packt is also known for their support to Open Source. They support Open Source projects through a project royalty donation. They already have contributed over 300,000. For this special occasion, they will allocate 30,000 to share between projects and authors in their own way that will be disclosed on the website soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more information about Packt Publishing, their books or how to sign-up for a free account for this offer, you can view the official website: &lt;a title="http://www.packtpub.com" href="http://www.packtpub.com" target="_blank"&gt;http://www.packtpub.com/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Books</category><category>Programming</category><category>Promotion</category><category>Releases</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2012/09/packt-publishing-thousandth-book-celebration.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 19 Sep 2012 18:44:44 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>EDDI Compiler 1.1.1  Dynamic Memory Allocation and Constructors/Destructors</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2012/07/eddi-compiler-1-1-1-dynamic-memory-allocation-constructors-destructors.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;As I'm in holiday, the work is going pretty fast.The&lt;strong&gt;version 1.1.1&lt;/strong&gt;of the&lt;strong&gt;EDDI Compiler&lt;/strong&gt;(eddic) is available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This version introduces two major changes. The first is the support of dynamic memory allocation. You can allocate a struct or a standard type in help using the new operator. The memory can be released using the delete operator. Another related improved is the addition of constructors and destructors to the language. The following sample shows what can be done with the new features:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;struct&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;A&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="k"&gt;this&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;){&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="k"&gt;this&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

        &lt;span class="n"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;"Constructed"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="o"&gt;~&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;this&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(){&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="n"&gt;println&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;"Destructed"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="kt"&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;main&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(){&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;A&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;b&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;A&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;55&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;delete&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;b&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The constructor is called once the memory is allocated. The delete operator calls the destructor and then free the memory. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When a structure is allocated on the stack, the constructor is called at the declaration point and the destructor is called when the variable gets out of scope. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The memory manager is quite simple for now. Memory is allocated in blocks. Each block has a header indicating the size of the block and its availability. The size of the header is 8 bytes in 32 bits and 16 bytes in 64 bits. The free operation can be done in constant time by just setting the availability flag to false. The disadvantage of this technique is that all the blocks needs to be tested to find a free block. This can be slow in some situations. I will try to make a better version in the future. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For that, the memory model has been improved. All the offsets are now increasing and the stack addresses are set at the end of the block. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another interesting improvement of the language is the support of switch. For now, only switch on int is supported. Here is an example of a switch in EDDI:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;switch&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;){&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;case&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="n"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;"3"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;case&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;4&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="n"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;"4"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;case&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="n"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;"5"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;case&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;6&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="n"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;"6"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;default&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="n"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;"default"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The performances of the optimizer have been improved, by doing live-variable analysis less often. Pointers can now be passed in registers. Some of the variables used as temporary copies are removed &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The peephole optimizer has been improved to use conditional move when possible. Moreover, the peephole optimizer is now able to perform some local copy propagation. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Future work&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next version of the EDDI Compiler will be the version 1.1.2. This version will add features to read the command-line. Moreover, it will also add support for char type and string comparisons. With that, I think that the language will start to be usable for toy applications. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There  will be some improvements to the code that have been left aside for a too long time. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Download&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can find the EDDI Compiler sources on the Github repository: https://github.com/wichtounet/eddic&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The exact version I refer to is the v1.1.1 available in the GitHub tags or directly as the release branch.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>C++</category><category>Compilers</category><category>EDDI</category><category>Releases</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2012/07/eddi-compiler-1-1-1-dynamic-memory-allocation-constructors-destructors.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 30 Jul 2012 10:18:01 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>EDDI Compiler 1.0.3 - Inlining and register allocation</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2012/07/eddi-compiler-1-0-3-inlining-register-allocation.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;The&lt;strong&gt;version 1.0.3&lt;/strong&gt;of the&lt;strong&gt;EDDI Compiler&lt;/strong&gt;(eddic) is available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only improvement to the language is that the size of a global array can now be defined using a constant global variable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main improvement of this version is the addition of &lt;strong&gt;inlining&lt;/strong&gt; in the optimization engine. This optimization replace a call to a function by the body of the function. For now, the inlining optimizer is quite basic. For now, it doesn't inline only a specific call site but all the call sites of a given function. Moreover, the heuristics used for inlining are quite simple (only the size of the function is taken into account). Only functions that takes int and float parameters can be inlined. This optimization will be improved in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second main change is the arrival of a &lt;strong&gt;basic register allocation&lt;/strong&gt;. In each function, one or more variables can be assigned to registers. Only the most used variables are allocated into registers. Another optimization is that variables that are not used after all optimization techniques have been applied are removed from the function storage. The unused functions are also removed from the program after the optimization passes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, the performances of optimization engine have been improved by about 20%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The MTAC representation has been improved. The ARRAY operators have been removed because they can be replaced with the DOT operators. The preamble and prologue generations for LTAC has also been refactored. When it is possible, the stack frames are not generated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, the configuration of the compiler has been improved with several new optimization option and the options being separated into several option groups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Future work&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next version of the EDDI Compiler will be the&lt;strong&gt;version 1.1.0&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main change will be member functions inside of structures. For now, there will be no kind of virtual functions and inheritance but that will certainly come in its time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And as ever, I will be more than pleased to hear any idea you could have about this project :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Download&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can find the compiler sources on the Github repository:&lt;a title="eddic on GitHub" href="https://github.com/wichtounet/eddic"&gt;https://github.com/wichtounet/eddic&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The exact version I refer to is the v1.0.3 available in the GitHub tags or directly as the release branch.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>C++</category><category>Compilers</category><category>EDDI</category><category>Optimization</category><category>Releases</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2012/07/eddi-compiler-1-0-3-inlining-register-allocation.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 14 Jul 2012 06:46:15 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>taskwarrior-php 0.1 : A simple PHP Frontend for Taskwarrior</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2012/07/taskwarrior-php-frontend-0-1.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I released the version 0.1 of &lt;strong&gt;taskwarrior-php&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project is a simple PHP Frontend for Taskwarrior. For now, the frontend is quite basic. All the tasks are displayed and sorted by projects. The completion of each project is also computed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.baptiste-wicht.com/?attachment_id=2035" rel="attachment wp-att-2035"&gt;&lt;img class="size-medium wp-image-2035" title="taskwarrior-php Screenshot" src="http://baptiste-wicht.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/07/taskwarrior-php-1-300x271.png" alt="taskwarrior-php Screenshot" width="300" height="271"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can also insert a new task. For now, only the project and the description of the task can be modified.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Download&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The application is available on the Git repository :&lt;a href="https://github.com/wichtounet/taskwarrior-php"&gt;https://github.com/wichtounet/taskwarrior-php&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The installation is simple, you just have to put all the files in a folder of a PHP server. Then, you have to edit the config.php to set the location of your Taskwarrior files.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is necessary that the Taskwarrior files are on the PHP server as well. For that, you can use the FTP pull and push commands of Taskwarrior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don't hesitate to contact me if you have some ideas for this project or if you find some bugs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Linux</category><category>Releases</category><category>Tools</category><category>Web</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2012/07/taskwarrior-php-frontend-0-1.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 09 Jul 2012 07:21:14 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The site is now running WordPress 3.4</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2012/06/the-site-now-running-wordpress-3-4.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I just updated the site to run WordPress 3.4&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Normally, you should not see any differences as most of the new features of this version are in the admin side, but if you see something that doesn't work, don't hesitate to contact me.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Others</category><category>Releases</category><category>The site</category><category>WordPress</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2012/06/the-site-now-running-wordpress-3-4.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 24 Jun 2012 00:36:37 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Install Cinnamon in Linux Mint - A forked Gnome Shell</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2012/01/install-cinnamon-linux-mint.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the last Linux Mint version (12), the developers have introduced a set of extensions to the Gnome Shell, Mint Gnome Shell Extensions (MGSE).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, plugins can't do everything the developers want. So they forked Gnome Shell and started building their own shell : Cinnamon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the time of writing, the appearance of this new shell is similar to MGSE in Linux Mint 12, but with some differences : only one status bar, the left bottom menu was changed, notification bar in the bottom bar, ...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can try it on your Linux Mint right now :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;sudo apt-get update
sudo apt-get install cinnamon-session&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, you have to logout and select Cinnamon in the Logon screen as the desktop environment. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personally, I still prefer MGSE, because I like having two bars, but that will perhaps change with some more tests on Cinnamon. And you, what do you think about Cinnamon ? Or about MGSE ? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want more informations about this new shell, you can read &lt;a href="http://cinnamon.linuxmint.com/" title="Cinnamon Official Site" target="_blank"&gt;the official site&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Linux</category><category>Mint</category><category>Releases</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2012/01/install-cinnamon-linux-mint.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 05 Jan 2012 07:11:19 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>WordPress 3.3 Sonny released!</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2011/12/wordpress-3-3-sonny-released.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;WordPress 3.3 introduces some very interesting features, specially for the blogger itself.It includes a new drag-and-drop uploader, hover menus for the navigation, a new toolbar, improved co-editing support, and a new Tumblr importer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The admin interface has add a great cleanup too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More information on the official release notes :&lt;a title='Wordpress 3.3 "Sonny" released' href="http://wordpress.org/news/2011/12/sonny/" target="_blank"&gt;http://wordpress.org/news/2011/12/sonny/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I already updated the blog to Wordpress 3.3 and it looks great for now. For the first time, I didn't have to disable all the addons prior to updating. This time it worked directly :)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Releases</category><category>The site</category><category>Web</category><category>WordPress</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2011/12/wordpress-3-3-sonny-released.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 13 Dec 2011 00:39:39 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>EDDI Compiler 0.6.1 : Function return types</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2011/11/eddi-compiler-0-6-1.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I just released a new version of the EDDI Compiler : eddic 0.6.1&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a minor update with only one change on the language: the functions can now return something. The return values are returned in registers (&lt;strong&gt;%eax&lt;/strong&gt; for int and &lt;strong&gt;%eax:%ebx&lt;/strong&gt; for strings). At this time, it is not possible to return an array from a function.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other changes of this version are on the code base side. All the headers have been cleaned. There are less useless imports and the code is cleaner. Moreover, I also have rewritten the Readme in order to include more useful information in it. The parsing phase should be a little faster now and the assembly has been improved by using the POP instruction. The phases of checking have also been reordered. In the future, it's possible that several phases will be merged together for performance purposes, but for now, it's quite fast on my sample even the 2MB stress file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can now generate the Doxygen generation using make doc. The target is generated with CMake. At this time, the documentation is almost empty, but I will work on it on the next releases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next version will be a major release. I don't know what will be the changes for the language itself, but the compiler will use a new intermediate representation. It will use Three-Address-Code representation. This representation is simple and can be easily optimized. This will make easier the transformation from the AST to the assembly. At this time, the code of the intermediate compiler is very hard to maintain and contains a lot of logic. The switch to a new, simpler, intermediate representation will simplify the intermediate compiler.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find the EDDI compiler sources on the Github repository :&lt;a title="EDDI Compiler Repository" href="http://github.com/wichtounet/eddic"&gt;https://github.com/wichtounet/eddic&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The exact version I refer to is the v0.6.1 available in the github tags or directly as the release branch.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>C++</category><category>Compilers</category><category>EDDI</category><category>Releases</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2011/11/eddi-compiler-0-6-1.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 28 Nov 2011 07:45:54 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Linux Mint 12 (Lisa) released!</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2011/11/linux-mint-12-lisa-released.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Linux Mint 12 has just been released!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This new version includes a Gnome 3 using a specific extension MGSE (Mint Gnome Sheel Extensions) and a Gnome 2 UI (MATE). You will find also a lot of other improvements. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From several months, Linux Mint is the most used Linux distribution. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more informations, you can read &lt;a href="http://blog.linuxmint.com/?p=1889" title="Linux Mint 12 Lisa released!" target="_blank"&gt;the official announcement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Linux</category><category>Releases</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2011/11/linux-mint-12-lisa-released.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 26 Nov 2011 06:08:45 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>EDDI Compiler 0.6.0 : Arrays</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2011/11/eddi-compiler-0-6-0-arrays.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;This new version of the EDDI Compiler was faster to finalize than the previous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main feature of this release is the use of arrays. You can now use arrays in the EDDI code. You can declare global or local arrays and pass them as parameters to the function. In the assembly, there is certainly still some optimization to perform, but the code works well for now. A new loop is also available the foreach loop for arrays. The loop iterates through each element of the array. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also performed some new improvements in the compiler speed. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The local and global variables now have default values (0 for int and the empty string for strings). So you can omit the value in the declaration. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I removed the dependency to the C library with replacing malloc with a little memory allocation function I wrote myself. This function is very simple and only use sys_brk to allocate memory directly after the program. You cannot release the memory for now, but that was the same before. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The compiler is now able to warn you if you declare something and you don't use it (parameter, variable, function). Moreover, if you enable the optimization, the functions and variables that are not used will not be compiled. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I made a little fix to the print_integer function to handle negative numbers. Before that, they were printed but in two's complement, now they are printed in the negative form (-344 for example). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't know exactly yet what will be included in the next release of the EDDI Compiler. Probably this will be minor release with the inclusion of function return types, but I'm not sure yet. In the future, I also want to add some kind of structure to the program. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find the compiler sources on the Github repository : &lt;a title="EDDI Compiler Repository" href="http://github.com/wichtounet/eddic"&gt;https://github.com/wichtounet/eddic&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The exact version I refer to is the v0.6 available in the github tags or directly as the release branch.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>C++</category><category>Compilers</category><category>EDDI</category><category>Releases</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2011/11/eddi-compiler-0-6-0-arrays.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 21 Nov 2011 08:07:20 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>eddic 0.5.1 : Better assembly generation and faster parsing</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2011/11/eddic-0-5-1-better-assembly-generation-and-faster-parsing.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I'm very pleased to release the version 0.5.1 of the EDDI Compiler.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It makes now a long time since the last version of eddic, but I started again working frequently on it. This version doesn't add any new feature to the language, but there are a lot of improvements in the compiler itself. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, the generated assembly has been improved a lot. I use now a intermediate representation of assembly and then the compiler is able to make more optimizations in its choice. This optimization is especially visible for integer computations. Before this, all the computations used stack operations and then we use almost only registers when it's possible. It's still not perfect, but it uses way less instructions. Moreover, this can enable me to write a 64 assembly code instead of 32 and provide both versions in the compiler. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another improvement is the speed of the parser. I now use Boost Spirit to parse the source file and construct an Abstract Syntax Tree. This parsing is very fast now (with some optimizations). Moreover, it will be easier to add new constructs later. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also improved the general performances at some places. I also use Boost Program Options to parse the command line options. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the next version (0.6.0), I will introduce arrays of int and strings and the foreach construct for array. I will also remove the dependency to malloc writing a memory allocation manager in assembly. I will also introduce warnings in the compiler. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find the compiler sources on the Github repository : &lt;a title="EDDI COmpiler Repository" href="http://github.com/wichtounet/eddic"&gt;https://github.com/wichtounet/eddic&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The compiler now needs Boost 1.47.0 to build. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The exact version I refer to is the v0.5.1 available in the github tags or directly as the release branch.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Assembly</category><category>Boost</category><category>C++</category><category>EDDI</category><category>Performances</category><category>Releases</category><category>templates</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2011/11/eddic-0-5-1-better-assembly-generation-and-faster-parsing.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 10 Nov 2011 03:33:32 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>EDDIC 0.5 : Functions and foreach</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2011/10/eddic-0-5-functions-foreach.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I'm pleased to release the version 0.5. of the EDDI Compiler.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This new version introduced the first version of function calls. The function can take several parameters but cannot return anything at this moment. A version of foreach loop is now available in the language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can also declare variables globally in the source code. The global variables are stored in the .data section of the ELF file and the local variables are stored on the stack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The error reporting of the compiler has been improved. Indeed, now the syntactical errors are reported with the exact location of the source.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are also a lot of improvements in the source code. The big header files have been splitted into several files. I replaced all the pointers by smart pointers that allowed me to remove all the memory leaks of the applications and to simplify the memory management. Finally, I started using some new features of C++11 to improve the source code of the application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next version will certainly see return types for functions and perhaps a first version of switch case. Moreover, I have a lot of improvements to do at the assembly level. Indeed, the generated assembly is not efficient at all. Perhaps, I will consider adding arrays too to this version.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find the compiler on the Github repository : &lt;a title="EDDI COmpiler Repository" href="http://github.com/wichtounet/eddic"&gt;https://github.com/wichtounet/eddic&lt;/a&gt;. If you watch the repository, you'll see that I followed a new branching model, the one proposed and enforced by the git-flow tool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The exact version I refer to is the v0.5 available in the github tags.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>C++</category><category>C++11</category><category>EDDI</category><category>Git</category><category>Releases</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2011/10/eddic-0-5-functions-foreach.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 10 Oct 2011 00:38:50 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>EDDI 0.4.1 : Loops and better assembly generation</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2011/07/eddi-0-4-1-loops-and-better-assembly-generation.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I just released the 0.4.1 version of the EDDI compiler.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This version introduce two kind of loops :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the while loop&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the for loop, in its general form with three expressions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, you can now use parenth in mathematical expressions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's it for the new features, but the compiler has been greatly improved. Now the scope of variables is managed, so you can have twice the same variables as long as they are not visible at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the assembly, there have been many improvements. The variables are not stored in a more efficient way, the concatenation of strings has been improved to take less space and other little changes have been made. The Lexer has been rewritten using a Scanner to manage the source file directly so that the error do now give the line and the column of the error source. The Parser and the Compiler itself have had some refactorings, but nothing really big.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find the compiler on the Github repository :&lt;a href="https://github.com/wichtounet/eddic"&gt;https://github.com/wichtounet/eddic&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The exact version I refer to is the v0.4.1 available in the github tags.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next version will certainly see more loops versions, some assembly refinements and perhaps first kind of function calls. I will also try to escalate the Token information in order to have better reporting when there aresemanticerrors. I will also some refactorings in the parse node to have a better integration of the Condition and the StringPool.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Assembly</category><category>C++</category><category>EDDI</category><category>Releases</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2011/07/eddi-0-4-1-loops-and-better-assembly-generation.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 28 Jul 2011 07:06:50 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>EDDI 0.4 : Native compilation and swap operator</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2011/07/eddi-0-4-native-compilation-swap.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;The version 0.4 of EDDI is released. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is only one new feature, the swap operator () to swap two variables together, but the biggest news is that now EDDI is not anymore an interpreted language, but is a compiled language. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, I rewritten the compiler in order to output Linux assembly code. For now the code is only 32 bits, but I plan to support 64 as well. I made that change in order to not having to write a virtual machine and in order to learn assembly as well. The current outputted assembly code is not really optimized and there will certainly be a lot of changes. Indeed, in order to simplify the switch to native compiler, I continued using stack operations, so that the numeric computations have a lot have a lot of stack operations in it. Moreover, I'm far from being a professional in assembly, so that, they can beginner's errors in the generated code. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use as to compile the assembly and then gcc to link. I will try to not depend on gcc, but it seems to be difficult if I want to use malloc (used for the string concatenation). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can download the sources and find some information on the GitHub repository : https://github.com/wichtounet/eddic/ (check the tag v0.4 if you want the exact version I refer in this post). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do not hesitate to send me your comments about the C++ code, the design or the outputted assembly. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first version will see loops integrated, certainly some assembly optimizations and some code refactorings I planned.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Assembly</category><category>C++</category><category>EDDI</category><category>Intel</category><category>Releases</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2011/07/eddi-0-4-native-compilation-swap.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 20 Jul 2011 07:27:13 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>EDDI 0.3 - Branches and conditions if, else if, else</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2011/07/eddi-0-3-branches-conditions.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I just pushed a new version of EDDI on the Git repository : EDDI 0.3&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This new version adds a new big features : Branches and condition. You can now use else / else if / else statements in EDDI code. So that a code like that will be executed :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;3&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;){&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;Print&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;"That's true. "&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;){&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;Print&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;"Try again"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;else&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;Print&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;"Good job"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;){&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;Print&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;"Not correct..."&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;else&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;6&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;){&lt;/span&gt; 
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;Print&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;"Right"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;and will give an output like this one : &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;
That's true. 
Good job
Right
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, there is no optimization made on the branches or the condition. I'm planning to make optimization when the condition doesn't depend on a variable so that I can automatically chose the good branch to execute. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To implement that branches, I use a common system with jumps and labels. The labels are special bytecode instructions read by the virtual machine and indicating the address of the next instruction. The condition are putting a 1 or a 0 on the stack and the JUMP_IF_NOT bytecode jump if there is a zero on the stack. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the next feature of the language, I plan to add a for loop. But I'm currently thinking of stopping the development of the virtual machine and output directly assembly code instead of bytecode. Because I want to concentrate on the compiler and I don't care about portability in this particular case. Moreover, this will force me to learn deeply assembly code and enable me to make more optimization. But nothing is sure at this moment. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sources are available on Github : &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The compiler, eddic : https://github.com/wichtounet/eddic/&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The virtual machine, eddivm : https://github.com/wichtounet/eddivm/&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;A commons library used by the two projects : https://github.com/wichtounet/eddi-commons/&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to see the exact version reffered to in this subject, you can select the tag v0.3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>C++</category><category>EDDI</category><category>Releases</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2011/07/eddi-0-3-branches-conditions.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 07 Jul 2011 06:42:21 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>