<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>Blog blog("Baptiste Wicht"); (Posts about The site)</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/</link><description></description><atom:link rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" href="http://baptiste-wicht.com/categories/the-site.xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 04 Jun 2017 20:17:46 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>New design: Faster and mobile compatible</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2016/11/new-design-faster-and-mobile-compatible.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I've finally taken the time to improve the design of the website!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The site was becoming slower and slower, the design was not responsive at all
and was an horror on mobile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've changed the design to focus more on content and removed superfluous things
such as the Google profile or slow things such as the 3D tag cloud. Moreover,
the design is now responsive again. It was a matter of removing a lot of bad
things I did in the CSS. Instead of having a vertical and an horizontal bars,
I now have only one vertical bar with both the navigation and a bit more
information. With these changes, the design is now also working on mobile phone!
It's about time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, I've also spent quite some time working on the speed of the website.
For this, I've bundled most of the JS and CSS files together and reduced them.
Moreover, the static files are now hosted and cached by CloudFlare. I've also
removed the 3D tag cloud which was quite slow. The Google API usage for the
Google profile badge were also quite slow. Overall, the index page is now really
fast. The article pages are also much faster but it's not perfect, especially
because of Disqus that does tons of requests and redirects everywhere. I've also
got rid of the Disqus ads which were really insignificant in the end. It may
take a while for the ads to disappear according to Disqus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know that it's still not perfect, but I hope that user experience on the blog
is now improved for all readers and now article can be read on mobile normally.
I'll try to continue monitoring the speed and usability of the website to see if
I can improve it further in the coming days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have any issue on the updated website, don't hesitate to let me know
either by commenting on this post or sending me an email (check the Contact
page).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Performance</category><category>The site</category><category>Web</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2016/11/new-design-faster-and-mobile-compatible.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 28 Nov 2016 06:55:48 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Upgrade to Nikola 7</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2015/11/upgrade-to-nikola-7.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I've finally taken the time to upgrade the website to Nikola 7 (it is about time, I know...).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The migration worked flawlessly, I simply had to update configuration to migrate deprecated and renamed tags and it worked really well. I also had to add a comma to the COMPILERS list because of the use of Python 3.3 now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you may have seen, I haven't posted in a while. I had quite some work for my thesis as well as for the courses I give at my school and I started playing Path Of Exile with took quite a bit of my free time :) I'll try to give some updates on the project I'm working on to make this blog live again.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Nikola</category><category>Personal</category><category>The site</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2015/11/upgrade-to-nikola-7.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 20 Nov 2015 09:56:32 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Related posts on a Nikola website</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2014/04/related-posts-nikola-website.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;The one thing I missed in Nikola was the lack of &lt;strong&gt;Related Posts generation&lt;/strong&gt;. I solved this during &lt;a href="http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2014/03/migrated-from-wordpress-to-nikola.html"&gt;the migration from WordPress to Nikola&lt;/a&gt;, by using simple algorithms to generate related posts for each blog post and then display them in the form of a simple widget. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, you can see the related posts of this post on the left, just under my Google+ badge. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the workflow that is used: 
 * A simple C++ tool generate a list of related posts in HTML for each posts
 * The generated HTML code is included in the MAKO template using Python&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this article, I'll show how the related posts are generated and how to include them in your template.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Related Post Generation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is important to note that it is necessary to cleanup the content of the files before using it: 
 * First, it is necessary to remove all HTML that may be present in the Markdown files. I remove only the HTML tags, not their content. For instance, in &lt;em&gt;&amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;test&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;&lt;/em&gt;, test would be counted, but not strong. The only exception to that, is that the content of preformatted parts (typically some or console output) is completely removed.
 * It is also necessary to cleanup Markdown, for instance, parentheses and square brackets are removed, but not their content. Same goes for Markdown syntax for bold, italics, ...
 * Finally, I also remove punctuation. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My related posts algorithm is very simple. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, I compute the Term Frequency (TF) of each word in each post. The number of times a word is present in a document is represented by &lt;em&gt;tf(w,d)&lt;/em&gt;. I decided to give a bigger importance to words in the title and the tags, but that is just a matter of choice. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After that, I compute the Inverse Document Frequency (IDF) of each word. This measure allows to filter words like: a, the, and, has, is, ... These words are not really representative of the content of a blog post. The formula for idf is very simple: &lt;em&gt;idf(w) = log(N / (1+ n(w)))&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;n(w)&lt;/em&gt; is the number of posts where the word is present. It is a measure of rarity of a word on the complete posts set. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once we have the two values, we can easily compute the TF-IDF vectors of each blog post. The TF-IDF for a word is simply: &lt;em&gt;tf_idf(w,d) = tf(w, d) * idf(w)&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, we can derive the matrix of Cosine similarities between the TF-IDF vectors. The idea of the algorithm is simple: each document is represented by a vector and then the distance between two vectors indicates how related two posts are. The formula for the Cosine similarity is also simple: &lt;em&gt;cs(d1, d2) = dot(d1, d2) / ||d1|| * || d2||&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;d1&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;d2&lt;/em&gt; are two TF-IDF vectors. Once the cosine similarities between each document is computed, we can just take the N most related documents as the "Related Posts" for each blog post. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this list, the C++ program simply generates an HTML file that will be included in each post by Nikola template. This process is &lt;strong&gt;very fast&lt;/strong&gt;. I have around 200 posts on this blog and the generation takes about 1 second. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Include in template&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the HTML files are generate, they are included into the website by altering the template and adding their content directly into the web page. Here is the code I use in &lt;em&gt;base.tmpl&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="cp"&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;post&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;and&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;not&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;post&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;source_link&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;startswith&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;'/stories/'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="x"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="x"&gt;    &amp;lt;div class="left-sidebar-widget"&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="x"&gt;        &amp;lt;h3&amp;gt;Related posts&amp;lt;/h3&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="x"&gt;        &amp;lt;div class="left-sidebar-widget-content"&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="x"&gt;            &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="cp"&gt;&amp;lt;%&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;os&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class="n"&gt;related_dir&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;os&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;getcwd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class="n"&gt;related_path&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;related_dir&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;post&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;source_link&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;".related.html"&lt;/span&gt;

                &lt;span class="k"&gt;try&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
                    &lt;span class="k"&gt;with&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;open&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;related_path&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;'r'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;as&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;f&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
                        &lt;span class="n"&gt;related_text&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;f&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;read&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
                        &lt;span class="n"&gt;f&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;close&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class="k"&gt;except&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ne"&gt;IOError&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;as&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;e&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
                    &lt;span class="n"&gt;related_text&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;"Not generated"&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class="cp"&gt;%&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="x"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="x"&gt;            &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="cp"&gt;${&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;related_text&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="cp"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="x"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="x"&gt;        &amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="x"&gt;    &amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="cp"&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;endif&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="x"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You could also display it in &lt;em&gt;post.tmpl&lt;/em&gt; as a simple list. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a limitation with this code: it only works if the source file has the same name than the slug, otherwise the file is not found. If someone has a solution to get the path to the source file and not the slug version, I'd be glad to have it ;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The code for the generator is available on the &lt;a href="https://github.com/wichtounet/wichtounet.github.io/tree/master/src/related"&gt;Github repository of my website&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wrote it in C++ because I don't like Python a lot and because I'm not good at it and it would have taken me a lot more time to include it in Nikola. If I have time and I'm motivated enough, I'll try to integrate that in Nikola. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope that could be useful for some people. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Algorithm</category><category>C++</category><category>Nikola</category><category>Python</category><category>The site</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2014/04/related-posts-nikola-website.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 05 Apr 2014 14:16:45 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Migrated from Wordpress to Nikola</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2014/03/migrated-from-wordpress-to-nikola.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;As you're reading this post, the site has been migrated from WordPress to &lt;a href="http://www.getnikola.com/"&gt;Nikola&lt;/a&gt; and is now hosted on Github. Nikola is a static site generator. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Reasons of the migration&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had several reasons to migrate my website from WordPress to a static site generator: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I was getting tired of WordPress. It not a bad tool, but it is becoming heavier and heavier. I think that one of the biggest problems is that you need tons of plugins to make a fully-functional blog. I had more than 20 plugins. And each time you upgrade WordPress, you run into problems with the addons. In my opinion, while I understand why you need plugins for syntax highlighting for instance, you should not need any plugin for performances or security. Moreover, when you think of it a blog is not dynamic, I write less than a post a week and most bloggers write about once a day, in the computer science's sense, it is not dynamic at all. So why bother with a database ?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I wanted to use my favourite tools for modifying my blog: the shell and vim. I don't think that wysiwyg editors are really adding any value to editing. I am faster writing posts in vim than I'm in a web editor. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I wanted to be able to edit my website offline. With a static generator, as long as you have the files on your computer, you can edit your site and even browse it offline. You can then deploy it on the internet later when you are online. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I wanted to host my blog at Github Pages, for fun! Moreover, I had some uptime issues with my host with quite some downtime in the last months. And it saves me some bucks each year, at least it was not a strong factor. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The quest for a good static blog generator&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has been several months already since I started thinking about migrating my blog. I had quite a hard time to find a suitable blog generator. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I needed something: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Simple&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Completely usable in command line&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;With a WordPress import feature&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fast: I didn't wanted to spend a long time generating the website. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Actively developed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem is that there are tens of static site generator. I considered several of them. The most well known is Jekyll. It really looks fine, but I have to say that I HATE Ruby. I think it is an horrible language with an even more horrible environment. I cannot even have Ruby installed on my computer. So I didn't spend a long time considering Jekyll. I also considered Hyde, which is the evil brother of Jekyll, but I think that it was missing documentation to be completely usable for me. I also though of Pelican, but I was not convinced with it. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't know how, but at first I didn't found about Nikola. It was only after some time that I came across Nikola by pure luck. Once I came accross Nikola, I directly was convinced by it. Nikola is written in Python and has a large set of features but still keeps the whole think very simple. Generation of the website is pretty fast. Even though I don't like Python very much, I'm able to stand its environment and if necessary I can hack around a bit. I also considered Hyde, which is the evil brother of Jekyll, but I think that it was missing documentation to be completely usable for me. I also though of Pelican, but I was not convinced with it. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't know how, but at first I didn't found about Nikola. It was only after some time that I came across Nikola by pure luck. Once I found about Nikola, I directly was convinced by it. Nikola is written in Python and has a large set of features but still keeps the whole think very simple. Generation of the website is pretty fast. Even though I don't like Python very much, I'm able to stand its environment and if necessary I can hack around a bit. So I decided to try the complete migration. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The migration&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once I decided to migrate to Nikola, I directly started by importing my WordPress site into a Git repository. This process is quite simple, you just have to export and XML dump from WordPress and then import it into Nikola with the *import_wordpress" command. This already downloads the necessary images and resources and create posts and pages corresponding to your site. It also generates some redirections from the old URL scheme to the new one. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, there is still some manual work to be done. Here is what I had to do after I imported my WordPress site into Nikola: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As syntax highlighting was done by a plugin, I had to convert it to Markdown myself. This was quite easy, just a matter of &lt;em&gt;sed&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I was not satisfied with the default templates so I enhanced it myself. As I'm a very poor web developer and even poorer web designer, it took me a long time, even if it is a simple one. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I wanted to add some visibility to the comments, so I used Disqus API to create Most Popular and Recent Comments widgets. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I had to create some redirections by myself for the tags and categories. This was again just a matter of simple shell commands. I filled a bug about it so it'll probably be fixed in the near future.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I tried to improve the performances of the generated website, but I'm still gonna work on this later, the calls to Disqus and Google javascripts are the ones that takes the most of the load time. I think that a static site could be even faster. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finally, I really missed the options to have related posts generated for each posts, so I hacked a simple way to include them for each posts. The related posts are generated using a very simple algorithm. I'll soon write a post about how I have done this. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Except from these things, it hasn't been too hard to migrate to Nikola. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until now I'm really satisfied with Nikola and I hope this will motivate me to write more blog posts in the coming months. I hope you'll find the website as enjoyable as before (or even more :) ). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are interested, you can read the &lt;a href="http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2014/03/migrated-from-wordpress-to-nikola.wp"&gt;source of this blog post&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though I tried my best to avoid 404 or problems with the new site, I'm pretty sure there will be some issues in the following weeks. If you happen to found a dead link or some part of the website is not working for you, don't hesitate to comment this post and I'll my best to fix it. If you have suggestions on how to improve the site or have a question about the process of migrating a website from Wordpress to Nikola, I'd be glad to answer you. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Nikola</category><category>Personal</category><category>The site</category><category>WordPress</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2014/03/migrated-from-wordpress-to-nikola.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 23 Mar 2014 21:23:21 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Back in Berkeley, California</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2012/09/back-in-berkeley-california.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I arrived yesterday to Berkeley, California.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just like I did my Bachelor thesis in Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory (LBNL), I will do my Master Thesis there too. The thesis will last a bit less than a semester.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During my Master Thesis I will try to use profiling samples from the Linux perf tools in GCC or Clang to optimize processor cache usage (avoid cache and page faults).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will try to publish some posts about that during the semester if I have time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Compilers</category><category>gcc</category><category>Others</category><category>Personal</category><category>The site</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2012/09/back-in-berkeley-california.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 13 Sep 2012 08:35:43 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The site is now running WordPress 3.4</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2012/06/the-site-now-running-wordpress-3-4.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I just updated the site to run WordPress 3.4&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Normally, you should not see any differences as most of the new features of this version are in the admin side, but if you see something that doesn't work, don't hesitate to contact me.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Others</category><category>Releases</category><category>The site</category><category>WordPress</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2012/06/the-site-now-running-wordpress-3-4.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 24 Jun 2012 00:36:37 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Enhanced Code Snippets with SyntaxHighlighter Evolved</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2012/03/enhanced-code-snippets-syntaxhighlighter-evolved.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;After a long time of service, I decided to replace the old WP-Syntax plugin with a more modern one: &lt;a href="http://wordpress.org/extend/plugins/syntaxhighlighter/" title="SyntaxHighlighter Evolved"&gt;SyntaxHighlighter Evolved&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought that the style of the code snippets of WP-Syntax started looking a bit old. The new plugin has several advantages:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The code snippets look better&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;A useful toolbar is available on each snippet allowing you to copy the code, to print it or to view the source only&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The configuration is more complete&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This plugin use the &lt;a href="http://alexgorbatchev.com/SyntaxHighlighter/" title="SyntaxHighlighter JavaScript package by Alex Gorbatchev"&gt;SyntaxHighlighter JavaScript package by Alex Gorbatchev&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is an example using this new plugin: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;ExecutorService&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;threadPool&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Executors&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="na"&gt;newFixedThreadPool&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;4&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="n"&gt;CompletionService&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;lt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;String&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;gt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;pool&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;ExecutorCompletionService&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;lt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;String&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;gt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;threadPool&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;lt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;10&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;++){&lt;/span&gt;
   &lt;span class="n"&gt;pool&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="na"&gt;submit&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;StringTask&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;());&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;lt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;10&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;++){&lt;/span&gt;
   &lt;span class="n"&gt;String&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;result&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;pool&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="na"&gt;take&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;().&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="na"&gt;get&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;

   &lt;span class="c1"&gt;//Compute the result&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="n"&gt;threadPool&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="na"&gt;shutdown&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For now, only two posts are using this new plugin:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.baptiste-wicht.com/2012/03/cpp11-concurrency-part1-start-threads/" title="C++11 Concurrency – Part 1 : Start Threads"&gt;C++11 Concurrency – Part 1 : Start Threads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.baptiste-wicht.com/2012/03/cp11-concurrency-tutorial-part-2-protect-shared-data/" title="C++11 Concurrency Tutorial – Part 2 : Protect shared data"&gt;C++11 Concurrency Tutorial – Part 2 : Protect shared data&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other ones are still using the old plugin. I will convert the other posts when I will find some time. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope that this change will makes the site better for you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>The site</category><category>Web</category><category>WordPress</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2012/03/enhanced-code-snippets-syntaxhighlighter-evolved.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 30 Mar 2012 06:53:48 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>A new theme for the site</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2012/03/a-new-theme-for-the-site.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I changed the theme on the site. I used the Sleek theme from Studiopress. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main reason to change to this theme was that I replaced some of my addons. For example, the breadcrumbs are already included in the theme. There is also an included widgets for Twitter. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another reason is that I find this theme more good looking than the hold one. And finally, this new theme is more up-to-date.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope that you will find this theme adapted. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've still some work to do adapting this theme for the site. If you encounter any kind of problems with the new design, don't hesitate to let a comment or to contact me.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>The site</category><category>Web</category><category>WordPress</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2012/03/a-new-theme-for-the-site.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Mar 2012 04:05:49 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Merry Christmas</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2011/12/merry-christmas.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;A bit late, but better late than never : Merry Christmas to all the readers of this blog :)&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>Others</category><category>Personal</category><category>The site</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2011/12/merry-christmas.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Dec 2011 00:12:57 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>WordPress 3.3 “Sonny” released!</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2011/12/wordpress-3-3-sonny-released.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;WordPress 3.3 introduces some very interesting features, specially for the blogger itself. It includes a new drag-and-drop uploader, hover menus for the navigation, a new toolbar, improved co-editing support, and a new Tumblr importer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The admin interface has add a great cleanup too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More information on the official release notes : &lt;a title='Wordpress 3.3 "Sonny" released' href="http://wordpress.org/news/2011/12/sonny/" target="_blank"&gt;http://wordpress.org/news/2011/12/sonny/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I already updated the blog to Wordpress 3.3 and it looks great for now. For the first time, I didn't have to disable all the addons prior to updating. This time it worked directly :)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Releases</category><category>The site</category><category>Web</category><category>WordPress</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2011/12/wordpress-3-3-sonny-released.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 13 Dec 2011 00:39:39 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>New Wordpress theme for the site</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2011/11/new-theme-site.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;After a long time with the old F2 theme, I decided to choose a more modern design. I chose the WP Plus design which is based on the Google Plus Design. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that this design is more practical and cleaner for the users and more comfortable. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, I also took some time to change some of my addons. I replaced All In One SEO with Wordpress SEO plugin from Joost de Valk. I think that this plugin is better than the first one, but more of that, it also replaced one addon generating the XML sitemap and helped me adding a breadcrumb to the site. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope that these changes will improve the user experience on my website. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you encounter any kind of problems with the new design, don't hesitate to let a comment or to contact me.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Personal</category><category>The site</category><category>Web</category><category>WordPress</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2011/11/new-theme-site.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 18 Nov 2011 00:56:17 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>No more ads on the site !</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2011/06/no-more-ads-on-the-site.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hi,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you have perhaps noticed, there is no more Google Adsense on the site. I removed them for several reasons :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;They were not really visually good&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;They slowed down the site by a factor of two&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;That gave a bad image of the site&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;This is not the main goal of the website to make money&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;They didn't made enough money to counter the previous disadvantages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So you will now have a faster and a bit nicer website to look at :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only page that contains ads on the site is the search because of the use of Google Custom Search that includes Google Ads, but this is not my ads. I will perhaps consider to add another search system in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope this will make the site more enjoyable&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;P.S. Is there is still a page with ads that I have forgotten to update, just let a comment with the URL of the page and I will remove the ads&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Google</category><category>Personal</category><category>The site</category><category>Web</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2011/06/no-more-ads-on-the-site.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 28 Jun 2011 06:33:07 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>This website is now running WordPress 3.1.3</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2011/06/this-website-is-now-running-wordpress-3-1-3.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I just made the update of this website to WordPress 3.1.3. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've had no problems with the update. But at the start the automatic updater throws me an Out Of Memory Error. But after disabling all my plugins, the automatic update had no problem to update my entire website without any errors :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don't hesitate to contact me (in the comments or via the contact form) if you found any problem on the website.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>The site</category><category>Web</category><category>WordPress</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2011/06/this-website-is-now-running-wordpress-3-1-3.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 02 Jun 2011 12:12:07 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Solve "File param is missing" problem of W3 Total Cache</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2011/06/solve-file-param-is-missing-problem-of-w3-total-cache.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;As you may have seen, my website had not CSS these last days. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was due to a bug in the W3 Total Cache plugin of Wordpress. The minified CSS file wasn't accessible. When we tried to access it from the site, there was an error : "File param is missing"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is an easy solution to solve this problem. You just have to disable the "Rewrite URL structure" option on the Minify tab in the W3 Total Cache options. This will solve the problems. The only issue with this solution, is that you will not have fancy links for your CSS and JS minified files, but I think it's a really little problem comparing to the lack of CSS :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hope this will be helpful to some of you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Performances</category><category>The site</category><category>Web</category><category>WordPress</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2011/06/solve-file-param-is-missing-problem-of-w3-total-cache.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 02 Jun 2011 07:42:27 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Now writing from Berkeley, California</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2011/05/now-writing-from-berkeley-california.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hi, &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This message has been written from California, where I'm for 3 months. I'm making my bachelor final project in Berkeley Labs. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll certainly give some informations about the project and my researches during the next months. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope that I'll have the time to write more articles this next months as I've made the last months... I had a lot of work at school and no motivation to write.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Others</category><category>Personal</category><category>The site</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2011/05/now-writing-from-berkeley-california.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 28 May 2011 20:38:43 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Holidays</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2010/08/holidays.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Monday, I will go on holidays for one week. I'll not have internet except on my smartphone, so I'll not post on this blog during one week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will just approve comments and perhaps answer to comments if this is necessary, but this is all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, to next week.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Others</category><category>Personal</category><category>The site</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2010/08/holidays.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 15 Aug 2010 10:37:52 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Wordpress 3.0 installed !</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2010/06/wordpress-3-0-installed.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Wordpress 3.0 (Thelounious) has been released this week. I just updated the blog with the new version. I had no problem during the upgrade process, all automatically. Good job !&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This major release of Wordpress solve more tan 1200 bug, add several performance improvements and add several new features :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Merge of Wordpress MU : You can now add several different blogs on the same installation of Wordpress&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;New default Theme : Twenty Ten&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Bulk updates for the plugins. You can updates all your plugins and themes at once.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt; More possibilities for the themes : custom background, headers, shortlinks, ...&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Custom post types&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Lighter interface&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want more information, this video can help you :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;embed src="http://v.wordpress.com/wp-content/plugins/video/flvplayer.swf?ver=1.21" type="application/x-shockwave-flash" width="640" height="360" wmode="transparent" seamlesstabbing="true" allowfullscreen="true" allowscriptaccess="always" overstretch="true" flashvars="guid=BQtfIEY1&amp;amp;width=640&amp;amp;height=360&amp;amp;locksize=no&amp;amp;dynamicseek=false&amp;amp;qc_publisherId=p-18-mFEk4J448M" title='Introducing WordPress 3.0 "Thelonious"'&gt;&lt;/embed&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Personal</category><category>The site</category><category>Web</category><category>WordPress</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2010/06/wordpress-3-0-installed.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 19 Jun 2010 07:07:59 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Welcome to my new website !</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2010/03/welcome-to-my-new-website.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Welcome to my new english website :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've moved all my english stuff from Developpez.com to make here a completely english website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope you'll find here some interesting stuff. I will publish articles and posts about Java, Spring, Swing, OSGi, Hardware and Web and perhaps others technologies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don't hesitate to say me what you think about this website.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Others</category><category>Personal</category><category>The site</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2010/03/welcome-to-my-new-website.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 17 Mar 2010 03:21:29 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>