<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>Blog blog("Baptiste Wicht"); (Posts about Windows)</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/</link><description></description><atom:link rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" href="http://baptiste-wicht.com/categories/windows.xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 04 Jun 2017 20:17:47 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Simplify Deep Learning Library usage on Linux and Windows!</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2016/04/simplify-deep-learning-library-usage-on-linux-and-windows.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;No, I'm not dead ;) I've been very busy with my Ph.D (and playing Path of Exile,
let's be honest...) and haven't had time to write something here in a long time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until now, there was too way to use my
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/wichtounet/dll/"&gt;Deep Learning Library (DLL)&lt;/a&gt; project:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write a C++ program that uses the library&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Install DLL and write a configuration file to define your network and the problem to solve&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first version gives you all the features of the tool and allows you to build
exactly what you need. The second version is a bit more limited, but does not
require any C++ knowledge. However, it still does require a recent C++ compiler
and build system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Due to the high C++ requirements that are not met by Visual Studio and the fact
that I don't work on Windows, this platform is not supported by the tool. Until
now!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've added a third option to use DLL in the form of a Docker image to make the
second option even easier and allow the use of DLL on Windows. All you need is
Docker, which is available on Linux, Mac and Windows. This is still limited to
the second option in that you need to write a configuration describing the
network, but you need to build DLL and don't need to install all its
dependencies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="usage"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Usage&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To install the image, you can simply use &lt;cite&gt;docker pull&lt;/cite&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code bash"&gt;&lt;a name="rest_code_70ecd1a9685f40f2991f1a5335e9990a-1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;docker pull wichtounet/docker-dll
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Then, to run it, you have to create a folder containing a &lt;cite&gt;dll.conf&lt;/cite&gt; file and
mount in the container at &lt;cite&gt;/dll/data/&lt;/cite&gt;. There are some examples in the
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/wichtounet/docker-dll/"&gt;image repository&lt;/a&gt;.  For instance,
on Linux from the cloned repository:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code bash"&gt;&lt;a name="rest_code_43234d0dbb9b46f49cb3f7de329b4d97-1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;docker run -v &lt;span class="si"&gt;${&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;pwd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;/rbm_mnist/:/dll/data/ wichtounet/docker-dll
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;or on Windows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code bash"&gt;&lt;a name="rest_code_29727ffcf5f645a7bab2f02b14948649-1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;docker run -v /c/Users/Baptiste/rbm_mnist/:/dll/data wichtounet/docker-dll
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;This will automatically run the actions specified in the configuration file and
train your network.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="conclusion"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would really have thought this would be harder, but it turned out that Docker
is a very good solution to deploy multiplatform demo tools :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As of now, there is only support for mnist data format in the tool in this
form, but I plan to add basic CSV support as well in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope that this will help people willing to try the library with a simpler
usage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>deep learning</category><category>dll</category><category>Linux</category><category>Machine Learning</category><category>projects</category><category>Windows</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2016/04/simplify-deep-learning-library-usage-on-linux-and-windows.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 29 Apr 2016 10:48:18 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Why and how I completely left Windows for Linux</title><link>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2013/07/why-how-left-windows-for-linux.html</link><dc:creator>Baptiste Wicht</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;For years now, I always kept a dual-boot at home with a Linux system (currently Gentoo) and a Windows system. At work, I only use Gentoo. This week-end, I decided to completely remove it and migrate the applications I used on Windows to my Gentoo system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Why Windows ?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So first things first, why was I keeping the Windows system ? For several reasons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Games :) Unfortunately, most of the games I play are not natively compatible with Linux.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Office. I always liked Microsoft Office. As I hate OpenOffice/LibreOffice, I never wanted to remove it For schools we always had several teachers forcing us to use Microsoft document formats.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Hardware support. I always found that hardware support in Windows was great. Most of the time when you add new peripheral, there is nothing, it just works, which is great.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Applications. I always had some applications that I didn't found good enough Linux equivalents for. For instance, Newsleecher, iTunes or TaggedFrog.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, I work on Linux for years now and I would like to have to work on Windows again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;What Changed ?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This weekend I upgraded my hardware configuration (Motherboard, CPU and RAM). I was afraid that I had to reinstall my Linux configurations (because of Gentoo compiled with march=native), but I never thought that I would have to reinstall Windows. I turned out the contrary: my Gentoo installation worked just fine and my Windows totally crashed (BSOD at each startup). I finally made it through Windows after disabled AHCI mode on my motherboard, but then activation was invalidated (of course...) and online activation was not working. I decided to install the new chipset drivers and launch the Windows update and after that, Windows decided to boot without any USB support (WTF...). After that, I decided that Windows what not so great at all for   hardware support...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another reason I left Windows is Windows 8. I find that Window 7 was really great, but I really don't like Windows 8 and I would never have upgraded my Seven to it. Moreover, I recently bought Microsoft Office 2013 and it turned that I had to create an account at Microsoft to install it... Seriously ??? And moreover, it turned out to be worse thant Office 2010 (which, again, was great).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So all these reasons made me remove Windows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;How to migrate everything to Linux ?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, I had no problem with my data. Most of my data are on a personal NAS and the remaining is on Dropbox, so no problem on this side.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I still had some problems to resolve. First of all, I needed my games to run on Linux. I currently play only Diablo III. As I had received a year free of &lt;a title="Crossover" href="http://www.codeweavers.com/products/"&gt;Crossover&lt;/a&gt;, I decided to give it a try. Crossover is based on Wine and ensures that some software are running correctly under it and provide technical support. After some tuning, Diablo III was running almost flawlessly on my Gentoo machine :) Problem 1 solved. I will totally buy a license of Crossover, once my free year is over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I still add some applications to replace. I use iTunes as my main music player and library manager. Some time ago, I tried a lot of programs like Amarok/Rythmbox/Banshee, but I didn't liked them a lot and they were not running very well on large library of music files. This time, I tried &lt;a title="Clementine" href="http://www.clementine-player.org/"&gt;Clementine&lt;/a&gt;. Even if not very beautiful, it had all the features I needed and worked very well. I decided to stick with it. Another program I like a lot on Windows is TaggedFrog. It is a very simple program allowing to put tags on any file on the system and then search by tag on them. I haven't found a total equivalent. I first tried Tracker that is a Gnome project, but I was not satisfied with the search interface. After that, I tried the very simple &lt;a title="TMSU" href="http://tmsu.org/"&gt;TMSU&lt;/a&gt;. It is a command-line based tagging manager. All the tagging must be done in command line. In my case, it is not a problem, as I don't mind using the command-line and I don't tag files very often. What is very interesting about TMSU is that it can create a virtual file system (based on FUSE). In this file system, you have all your tags  as folder and you can see directly all the files of each tag. Moreover, you can directly make cross search (has tag X and Y and Z) by just going down in the tag folder. It is really great and has everything I needed. Finally, I also needed something to replace Newsleecher. I haven't found something as great (especially no replacement for the Supersearch function), but I installed &lt;a title="Sabnzbd" href="http://sabnzbd.org/"&gt;Sabnzbd&lt;/a&gt; which works really well and is very simple. For now, I just use the web interface and haven't installed any other front-end, but that will perhaps change in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I haven't replaced Office for now on. It occurred to me that since I left school, I haven't used it a lot, so that will probably not be a problem anymore. I will change to write the few letters I have to write on Latex and if I have Office documents, I'll probably read them on Google Drive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if I lost a lot of time with all that, I think it is a great think. It makes one less configuration to maintain and some less costs on the future. Moreover, I will save some time, because I won't have to switch between Linux and Windows for different tasks. And now, I have a second SSD ready for something else, either for RAID 1 to ensure redundancy on Linux or to mount on a server, I'll see later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will probably have some more problems in the future, but I'm convinced that there will be Linux solutions to it :)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Gentoo</category><category>Linux</category><category>Others</category><category>Personal</category><category>Windows</category><guid>http://baptiste-wicht.com/posts/2013/07/why-how-left-windows-for-linux.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2013 06:24:25 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>